<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Enochs walk and change opened in a sermon at Lawrence-Jury in London, Febr. 7th, 1655, at the funeral of the Reverend Mr. Richard Vines, minister of the Gospel there : with a short account of his life and death, with some elegies &amp;c. on his death / by Tho. Jacombe ...</title>
            <author>Jacombe, Thomas, 1622-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J115A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475746</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151189</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151189)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2248:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Enochs walk and change opened in a sermon at Lawrence-Jury in London, Febr. 7th, 1655, at the funeral of the Reverend Mr. Richard Vines, minister of the Gospel there : with a short account of his life and death, with some elegies &amp;c. on his death / by Tho. Jacombe ...</title>
                  <author>Jacombe, Thomas, 1622-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[10], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and E.M. for Ralph Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: Enochs change.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and tightly bound, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151189:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENOCHS WALK AND Change, Opened in a SERMON At <hi>Lawrence-Jury</hi> in LONDON, <hi>Febr.</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1655. AT THE FUNERAL Of the REVEREND Mr. <hi>RICHARD VINES,</hi> Miniſter of the GOSPEL. there. With a ſhort Account of his <hi>LIFE</hi> and <hi>DEATH.</hi> With ſome Elegies, &amp;c. on his death.</p>
            <p>By THO. JACOMBE, Miniſter of <hi>Martins-Ludgate</hi> in the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Edition.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ZECH. 1.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Your fathers, where are they? and the Prophets do they live for ever?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal Exchange. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_parishioners">
            <pb facs="tcp:151189:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151189:2"/>
            <head>To the Inhabitants of <hi>Lawrence-Jury,</hi> in the CITY of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured, and Beloved in our Lord Jeſus,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow many of our <hi>Starres</hi> in this City have of late <hi>fallen,</hi> or rather <hi>aſcended</hi> into a higher <hi>Orbe,</hi> I nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not tell you: What is your duty under this <hi>threatening</hi> Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, you alſo know; and it will be well if you <hi>do</hi> it as well as <hi>know</hi> it. The <hi>Eclipſes</hi> of glorious <hi>lights</hi>-have been as frequent and as ſad with you, as any; and I feare (whatever the <hi>over-daring A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers</hi> of our times do ſay from their Eclipſes, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze and terrifie us,) theſe do portend ſomething in a way of <hi>judgement.</hi> Tis not long ſince the <hi>violent axe</hi> bereaved you of one; a <hi>milder blow</hi> from God Himſelfe hath now taken away another, the Reverend Mr. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> an able and godly Miniſter; a man of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular worth; none but himſelf <hi>would deny</hi> it, none but himſelf <hi>could expreſſe</hi> it.</p>
            <p>I here preſent you with the <hi>Sermon,</hi> which not many weeks ago I preach'd at his <hi>Funeral.</hi> He was your <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour,</hi> called and preſented by your ſelves: whileſt he liv'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceived much love and encouragement from many of you; ſince God took him, your <hi>bounty</hi> and <hi>cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity</hi> hath been highly expreſſed to his ſad and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful widow, (for which I hope the Lord will abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requite you): whileſt I weighed theſe things with my ſelfe, I could not but make uſe of your <hi>Parochial
<pb facs="tcp:151189:3"/>body</hi> in this Dedication. But (alas!) in ſo poor and worthleſſe a Preſent, why do I ſo much trouble you or my ſelf about it?</p>
            <p>Give me leave to tell you, I was very unwilling to engage in this work; for though I looked upon it as very honourable, yet I judged my ſelf every way unfit for it. Importunity prevailed with me, and meerly that; And now 'tis done, let me aſſure you, many would have done it with <hi>more-ability,</hi> none with <hi>more affection</hi> to him who was your precious Miniſter, my loving Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and worthy friend.</p>
            <p>I was forc'd into the <hi>Pulpit</hi> then, and now unto the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> though I confeſſe more willingly, and with leſſe reluctancy; for though love to the <hi>perſon</hi> of the deceaſed could <hi>hardly</hi> make me <hi>preach,</hi> yet that being done, love to his <hi>name</hi> and <hi>memory</hi> did more eaſilie encline me to <hi>print.</hi> I look for many cenſures, but I muſt ſhadow my ſelf under the name of Mr. <hi>Vines.</hi> Well, ſuch as the Sermon is, you have it; and this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> doth not come to beg your <hi>Protection.</hi> (Alas, 'tis below envy, who will meddle with ſo harmleſſe and inconſiderable a thing) but your Acceptation, (and I hope your <hi>candour</hi>) will run parallel with Gods <hi>mercy,</hi> which accepts of <hi>goats haire,</hi> when no <hi>ſilver</hi> or <hi>gold</hi> can be brought.</p>
            <p>For the matter here handled, 'tis <hi>weighty</hi> and <hi>very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Mercy</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> are the two <hi>poles,</hi> upon which all Religion turnes; you have them both here ſet before you. Here's <hi>your duty</hi> in a <hi>holy life,</hi> here's <hi>Gods mercy</hi> in a <hi>happy death.</hi> If I be not miſtaken, it may be a word in <hi>ſeaſon</hi> to you. God hath endowed many of you with great parts and underſtanding; take heed of being <hi>headſtrong</hi> or <hi>top-heavy.</hi> Oh, walk humbly! God hath bleſſed you with great eſtates, you have <hi>pounds</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:151189:3"/>others <hi>pence,</hi> bleſſe God for it, but yet be above all theſe things. <hi>Walk</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and be <hi>Heavenly minded!</hi> your <hi>thouſands</hi> will be but <hi>ciphers</hi> when you come to <hi>die;</hi> your <hi>cheſts</hi> will not take away the <hi>feares</hi> of a <hi>coffin.</hi> Oh, do not loſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Power of Religion in the croud of worldly emploiments. You are a people that make Profeſſion of the wayes of God; look to ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. This is well; but ſee that <hi>Jacobs</hi> voice and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> hands go together. Let the great <hi>fervour</hi> of your ſpirits, appear in the intereſt of Religion, and in the concernments of Gods glory. I might runne over ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things which are here handled, which as I conceive, do hit you very right; (for indeed this Diſcourſe was not ſo much <hi>calculated</hi> for the <hi>meridian</hi> of the <hi>dead,</hi> as of the <hi>living</hi>) <hi>Reade</hi> and <hi>ponder,</hi> and <hi>the Lord give you a right underſtanding in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have taken the boldneſſe in the cloſure of my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to ſuggeſt a word or two to you by way of advice, which the ſad occaſion leads me to Again and again I would put you upon this, to look back upon the <hi>precious Labours</hi> of your <hi>removed</hi> and <hi>dead Ministers,</hi> and <hi>live</hi> up to them. The <hi>Sower</hi> is gone, but yet the <hi>ſeed</hi> may <hi>grow up.</hi> This your laſt deceaſed Miniſter was very averſe to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and we are very ſorry for it; what good might the Church of God have reaped, had he made publick his excellent notions by <hi>printing,</hi> (which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) yet we are not under deſpaire as to this,<note place="margin">Clem. Alexand. Strom l <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but that by the help of his <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>learned</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> A Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſe.</note> 
               <hi>friend,</hi> (once your Paſtour too) ſome of his Papers may ſee the light. But whether we have this mercy or not, you that were his <hi>Auditours</hi> and <hi>Pariſhioners,</hi> do you live ſo <hi>holily,</hi> ſo <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> ſo <hi>firmely establiſhed</hi> in the <hi>Truth,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> (which he was
<pb facs="tcp:151189:4"/>almoſt perpetually clearing up to you) that we may ſee his <hi>Sermons</hi> printed in your Lives. That's a bleſſed thing, when <hi>Ministers die,</hi> and their <hi>Sermons live,</hi> and are made <hi>publike</hi> in the carriage of them that heard them.</p>
            <p>I thought to have inſerted ſomething here, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>ſuddenneſſe</hi> of his <hi>death,</hi> upon which may be, ſome are too forward to paſſe ſtrange Interpretations. And this I thought the rather to do, becauſe I underſtand, in his own Pulpit one lately gave this as his obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſince <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayer, he had obſerved there was more <hi>ex tempore</hi> death, then ever there was before. But upon ſecond thoughts I blotted out all this as very unneceſſary. I ſhall only advertiſe you of one thing in order to the Sermon, and I have done. When I preach'd I reſolv'd I would not be tedious, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore omitted many things. Here I have taken the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to inſert them, as being very neceſſary to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in hand. And yet here too I have put them in with much brevity, without any great enlargement, leſt the work ſhould ſwell to too great a bulke,<note place="margin">Ne duplo te oneret minus ſuavis oratio, ſi &amp; longa fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit. <hi>Bern. de confid l.</hi> 1.</note> and ſo come to you rather as a Tractate then as a Sermon; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leſt it ſhould be doubly burdenſome, by its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity and weakneſſe too.</p>
            <p>I commit you to God, and to the Word of his grace, praying that your Miniſters here may ſee your faces with joy, and that you may ſee their faces with joy at the day of judgement. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant in Chriſt, <hi>THO. JACOMBE.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 12. 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151189:4"/>
            <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough of late yeares, this City hath been more freed then formerly, from the frights of wars, the noiſome peſtilence, and outward ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, yet the troubles of real Saints have been much increaſed, through the inundation of errours, hereſies and blaſphemies, too much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ulged. And this hath been no ſmall addition to our grief, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t many faithful, fruitful, Orthodox Miniſters, eminent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h for Learning and Piety, have by death been removed from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> now in the time when we moſt needed their counſel, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ching and prayers, for our preſent healing, and the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of our future feared dangers.</p>
            <p>Oh! how ſad a ſight is it, to behold our Pilots, our Steerſmen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng dead upon the deck, when the winds riſe, the ſeas ſwell, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> clouds blacken, and the Heavens lowre, preſaging approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſtormes: How awakening a Providence is this, to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> quarters beaten up, and at the ſame time to ſee our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s and Standard-bearers laid lifeleſſe in the duſt! We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> without ſorrow remember the death of many of our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es, whoſe ſignal characters of deſerved commendation have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eady been made publike for the uſe of ſucceeding Ages<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr</hi> Gouge. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Gataker. <hi>Mr</hi> Whitaker. <hi>Mr.</hi> Robinſon, &amp;c.</note>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d this our late blow received in the removal of famous Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> doth cauſe our former wounds to bleed afreſh.</p>
            <p>This Sermon preached at his Funeral, will give an account <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his great worth. Therein therefore we ſhall be the ſhorter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ugh by reaſon of our intimate acquaintance with him, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ld ſpeak very much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> His natural <hi>acumen,</hi> together with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> acquired abilities were extraordinary. He was a ſmart Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant,
<pb facs="tcp:151189:5"/>as it was obſerved in many places with admiration<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> not only in the Aſſembly of Divines againſt diſſenting Brethren, but likewiſe at the Conference at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> about the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of Prelacy, where ſome of his learned Oppoſites, ſtill living, were very ſenſible of his ſtrength. He was a well-ſtudied Orthodox Divine, his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry was ſolid, pithy, quick and ſearching, as his moſt judicious Auditors in <hi>Warwickſhire, Cambridge</hi> and <hi>London</hi> will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. His Sermon preached at the Funeral of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> doth prove him to be an excellent Rhetorician, an eloquent Oratour. The Sermons preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both Houſes of Parliament, do not only diſcover h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> high parts, but do tell the world that he was neither a flatter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> nor time ſerver. As he had a clear head, and could dive dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into a knotty controverſie, ſo he had (<hi>Luther</hi>-like) an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted ſpirit, and was not afraid of men, but could and would ſpeak his minde in any company, with brave mettal and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity. The great deſige of his Miniſtery, (eſpecially toward his end) was to drive man out of himſelf, and to draw him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt; to diſcover the cheats of mans deceitful heart, and to throw down all ſandy foundations of hope of Heaven; to encourage an humble dependance upon the Lord Jeſus, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo to quicken inſide holineſſe, with the Power of Godlineſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in a Chriſtian converſation.</p>
            <p>And (to adde that which was the Crown of all his other Excellencies) he was a man of a right gracious tender ſpirit whereof this was one demonſtration, (to inſtance in no more that he reſolved rather to ſuffer, by being turned out of the Maſterſhip of <hi>Pembroke</hi>-Hall in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> than to ſubſcribe the Engagement againſt his conſcience. Yea, he was (of our knowledge) a hearty Presbyterian, notwithſtanding the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſcouragements which are from every hand, caſt upon the death of this Worthy man, our much endeared Brother<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our words cannot ſufficiently expreſſe the grief of our own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hearts; And, to move others to mourning (beſides ſundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arguments which we will not mention,) we may truly apply ſome of the paſſages of <hi>Davids</hi> Lamentation) over <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:151189:5"/>and <hi>Jonathan. Weep over Saul, who cloathed you with ſcarlet, with other delights,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1</note> 
               <hi>who put on Ornaments of gold upon your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel. The bow of Jonathan returned not hack. They were ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then Lions.</hi> How profitable and pleaſant, how warm in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, how delightful in language, and how rich in notions was precious Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> in his Miniſtry! and with what irreſiſtible ſtrength was he wont to ſhoot arrowes of conviction into the conſciences of his Auditors? But alas alas, Now this Champion, this Prince of Preachers is laid ſilent in the duſt, (with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our reverend deceaſed Brethren) never any more to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to warm, to encourage, to edifie our ſouls by Miniſterial en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe by theſe doleful diſpenſations, the voice of the Lord ſpeaketh to the great City. <hi>Hear the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah 6.9</note> 
               <hi>and who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it.</hi> And becauſe there can be no evil in the City, and the Lord hath not done it,<note place="margin">Amos 3.6</note> therefore the Prudent will lay theſe things to heart.</p>
            <p>When the Miniſters of the Goſpel are decried as Antichriſtian by many, and ſlighted as uſeleſſe by the moſt, it is matter of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation; and ſhould be for a Lamentation, that at the ſame time God himſelf doth make ſuch great breaches, both in this City and ſeveral other Counties in the Nation, by taking to himſelf ſo many, and men ſo tranſcendently famous, for their ability and fidelity in the ſervice of his Church.</p>
            <p>And how can a gracious heart do leſſe upon ſuch ſad occaſions, then (groaning out its grief at Gods foot) make ſerious inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, what may be the cauſe of this his great diſpleaſure?<note place="margin">Deut. 29.24. Ezek. 20</note> As a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iſraelites the Sabbaths ceaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h becauſe they were deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; ſo, may not we ſuſpect that the number of worthy Miniſters in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>England</hi> is much abated<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe they are commonly undervalued?<note place="margin">Iſai. 5</note> The barrenneſſe of Gods Vineyard provoked him to deprive them of the influences of thoſe clouds, which before had watered them. The Lord Jeſus threatned to remove the Candleſtick with the light in it from the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.4, 5 Amos 8.5. with 10.11, 12</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had loſt her firſt love. And heretofore, a famine of hearing Gods Word was menaced, when holy Ordinances became burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and many more inſtances recorded in holy Story, do
<pb facs="tcp:151189:6"/>hint the cauſes of divine diſpleaſure, expreſſed by the death of ſo many worthy Miniſters.</p>
            <p>But it is much more eaſie in theſe our ſufferings, to diſcover the hand which inflicteth them, and the ſins which procure them, then to prevail with people, ſo ſeriouſly to ſet upon the work of Humiliation and Reformation, that the Almighty may be pacified towards us, and that theſe our ſad breaches may be ſanctified and repaired through his grace.</p>
            <p>Herein, his Majeſty help us and our Brethren in the Miniſtry, to be ſucceſſefully ſerviceable by our counſel, example and prayers, through the prevalent Interceſſion of our Lord and Saviour; in whom we are</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Soul-Friends and Servants, <hi>SIMEON ASHE. EDMUND CALAMY.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>March</hi> 10. 1655.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>All Mr. <hi>VINE</hi>'s Sermons are newly collected into one Volume, and printed for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> at the Sun againſt <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151189:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ENOCH'S WALK</hi> AND CHANGE: Opened in a SERMON Preached at the FU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERAL of the Reverend, Mr. <hi>RICHARD VINES.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 5.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, and he was not, for God took him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter is a ſhort, and yet a long Hiſtory; 'tis called, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>The Book of the generations of Adam;</hi> (that is) A Summary Deſcription of the <hi>Genealogies, Deſcents, Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of the old Patriarks, who lived in the firſt Age or Period of the world,<note place="margin">Uſhers <hi>Annal. de</hi> i. <hi>à mund. aetat</hi> Nisbets <hi>Script. Chronol.</hi>
               </note> from the Creation to the Flood (which ſpace of time conſiſted of 1656 years, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the general Computation of Chronologers: ſo that the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151189:7"/>world was then juſt as old from the Creation to the <hi>Floud,</hi> as now it is from he Incarnation of our Lord to this Age.) Amongſt theſe Ancients <hi>Enoch</hi> was one, and one of the beſt too, A Star of the firſt Magnitude, for he ſtands here upon record, commended <hi>for his walking with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Text you have him deſcribed,
<list>
                  <item>1. By his <hi>Holineſs</hi> or <hi>good Converſation, He walked with God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 By his <hi>Happineſſe</hi> or <hi>bleſſed Tranſlation; He was not, for God took him.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall (before I fall upon the matter it ſelf) premiſe a word or two concerning the <hi>Perſon.</hi> For the <hi>Perſon, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch,</hi> know there were two of this name;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> one was the <hi>ſon of Cain,</hi> of whom you reade, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.17. <hi>And Cain knew, &amp;c. and he builded a City, and called the name of the City after the name of his Son Enoch</hi> (which City,<note place="margin">Henochia haec conditarum ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium quotquot unquam fuerunt in or be terrarum prima &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquiſſima putatur. <hi>Druſ. Enoch cap. 3.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Druſius</hi> obſerves, was the firſt that ever was built in the world). The other was the ſon of <hi>Jared,</hi> of the line of <hi>Seth,</hi> of whom you reade in this Chapter, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.18. And this is the <hi>Enoch</hi> the Text ſpeaks of. <hi>How long he lived,</hi> the 23. verſe tells us, <hi>All the dayes of Enoch were</hi> 365 <hi>yeares: How he lived,</hi> the Text tells us, as alſo what became of him after his thus living; <hi>He walked with God, and was not, for God took him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>New Teſtament</hi> alſo takes notice of him, you have him in <hi>Lukes</hi> Genealogy, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.37. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks of him in his Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Judas frater Jacobi parvam quidem, quae de ſeptem Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicis eſt, Epiſtolam reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit; &amp; quia de libro He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch, qui Apoeryphus eſt, in ea aſſumit teſtimonia, cum pleriſque rejicitur. <hi>Hier. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Script. Eccl.</hi>
               </note> (the <hi>Divine Authority</hi> of which is not to be <hi>queſtioned,</hi> becauſe it mentions <hi>Enochs Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie,</hi> (concerning which there are ſo many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes amongſt the Learned) no more then ſome of <hi>Pauls Epiſtles</hi> are to be <hi>queſtioned,</hi> becauſe therein he cites <hi>common Authors,</hi> as <hi>Menander, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus, &amp;c.</hi>) <hi>And Enoch alſo the ſeventh from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, propheſied of theſe, ſaying, Behold, the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with ten thouſands of his Saints. Paul</hi> puts him amongſt his Worthies, as to faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5. <hi>By faith Enoch was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death, and was not found, becauſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151189:7"/>God had tranſlated him; for before his Tranſlation, he had this Testimony, that he pleaſed God.</hi> By the way, Where had hee this <hi>Testimony?</hi> I anſwer in my Text, for though in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew 'tis, He <hi>walked</hi> with God, yet the Greek Verſion reads it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sept.</note> He <hi>pleaſed</hi> God; and the Apoſtle, partly to honour this Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, and partly for the great uſe of the Greek <hi>language in that Age,</hi> doth here, and in ſome other places,<note place="margin">Vid. Capel. Crit. Sacr. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> leave the Hebrew and follow it; (yet from hence we muſt not inferre, that their Tranſlation is <hi>Authentick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amam Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb Bibl. l. <hi>1.</hi> Err. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and to be preferred before the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Text.) But here I digreſſe.</p>
            <p>Not to trouble you with the impertinent ridiculous fables of the Jewiſh Doctors concerning this <hi>Enoch;</hi> this is clear of him, He was a good man; and that too (<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Xenoph.</note> which adds much to his worth) hee was <hi>good</hi> when the times were <hi>bad.</hi>
               <note place="margin">R. Salomon ait Enoch ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum quidem fuiſſe, ſed mente instabili, ac ad impiè agendum propenſâ, ac prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea Dcum celeriter ac praematura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> morte eum ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuliſſe. <hi>Cartwr. in Gen.</hi> Vixit, dum vixit, laudabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter, quanquam ſunt qui eum inſimulant, levitatis &amp; inconstantiae. <hi>Druſ.</hi> Exibilandi Hebraei, qui tradunt Henoch ante tempus raptum, quòd levis &amp; lubricus eſſet, adeò non pudet eos, tam aperta mendacia divinare. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lvend.</hi>
               </note> He was like a fiſh that keeps his freſhneſſe in falt-water; like a found body that's healthfull in a peſt-houſe; the world was now overflown with a deluge of ſin, and was ſhortly to be overflown with a deluge of waters; but now <hi>Enoch walked with God,</hi> and he loſt nothing by it, for <hi>he was not, God tooke him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a future ſtate for man, diſtinct from this preſent ſtate.</hi> This is ſo great a truth, that God would have it known in all Ages, and therefore till the Word was written to reveal it, God will give ſome <hi>viſible ſpecimens</hi> of it. In the times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>flood, Enoch</hi> ſhall be thus <hi>tranſlated,</hi> as <hi>obſes &amp; teſtis u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vitae</hi> (ſo <hi>Tertullian</hi>) in the times after the Flood <hi>Elijah</hi> ſhal go to Heaven in a <hi>fiery Chariot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theodorus Quaeſt. in Geneſ, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Datâ ſententiâ mortis voluit Dominus ducere homines in ſpem vitae, quod fecit in patribus utriuſque ſtatûs, ſcilicet, Naturae, Legis, &amp; Gratiae. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde in primo ſtatu dedit ſpem evadendi neceſſitatem mortis, &amp; hoc eſt in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch, in Lege in Heliâ, in tempore Gratiae in Chriſto. <hi>Aquin.</hi> Videntes Habelem juſtum à Caino interfici, potuerunt aliquâ tentatione vexari, ſed cum poſteà pro ſuâ fide &amp; pietate ita Henochum aſſumi viderent, ſtatim judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care licuit, ſanctos &amp; crucem &amp; gaudia haec obituros, cum utrumque haec exempla oſtenderent. <hi>Pet. Martyr.</hi>
               </note> and ſo both Ages are inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in this weighty and fund amental Truth. This notion I had at firſt from a Divine of our own. But ſince, I find others before him did touch upon it.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151189:8"/>
            <p>But I come to the matter here laid down, <hi>Hee walked with God, &amp;c.</hi> Here is the ſumme of mans duty, and the <hi>zenith</hi> of Gods mercy. Here is the <hi>morning</hi> of Grace, and the <hi>mid-day</hi> of Glory. Here is the work of <hi>Earth,</hi> and the wages of <hi>Heaven.</hi> Here is a Chriſtians <hi>walk</hi> and <hi>reſt,</hi> and both with God.</p>
            <p>There are two <hi>General Propoſitions,</hi> or <hi>Doctrinal Obſervations</hi> that offer themſelves to us from the Text.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Propoſ. A true Chriſtians life is a walking with God. Enoch walked with God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Propoſ. A Chriſtians change is a going to God. He was not, for God took him.</hi> Here is Holineſſe and Happineſſe meeting in a narrow room, ſweetly kiſſing and embracing each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall only ſpeak to the firſt of theſe, and reduce the ſecond under that, by way of Motive.</p>
            <p>A true Chriſtians life (I ſay) is a <hi>walking with God.</hi> You have the ſame Character given to <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 6.9. <hi>He was a juſt man, and perfect in his generations.</hi> How doth that appear? it followes, <hi>And Noah walked with God.</hi> Take the phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in ſo many leters and ſyllables, it doth not often occur in the Scripture; but as to its ſenſe, and genuine import, there are <hi>many expreſſions</hi> which run <hi>parallel</hi> with it; but here I will not ſtay.</p>
            <p>There are two things in the Doctrine.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>A Chriſtians life is a walking.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Tis not every walking, but a walking with God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I might put them together, but for method ſake, I'le a little ſeparate them: and ſo my work ſhall be to ſhew you, 1. <hi>In
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151189:8"/>what reſpects a Chriſtians life is a Walking.</hi> Secondly, <hi>In what reſpects it is a walking with God.</hi> I'le name five particulars for each. For the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, A <hi>Chriſtians life is a Walking. His life is an active life.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Non-dicitur Henochum Deoastitiſſe, aſſediſſéve, ſed cum Deo ambuláſſe; certè igitur metu quodam, &amp;c. Sanè Peripatetici ſunt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles quique. <hi>Bp. Halis Enochiſm. Prov. 6.10 Gen. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Enoch</hi> did not ſtand ſtill, or ſit idle, or like <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſluggard,</hi> lie upon a bed of <hi>ſlothfulneſſe. Hee walked. The new born man is the active man;</hi> he beſtirs himſelf in the great concernments of Gods glory, and his own good. Grace is not an idle, ſleepy, drowſie habit, but an active, lively, operative thing: Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doth not make men <hi>loyterers,</hi> but <hi>labourers.</hi> In the <hi>ſweat</hi> of our <hi>browes</hi> the earth brings forth <hi>fruit to us,</hi> in the ſweat of our <hi>brows</hi> we bring forth <hi>fruit to God.</hi> The Chriſtians <hi>life</hi> is a <hi>pains-taking life;</hi> none have ſo much work as they, many duties to be performed, many ordinances to be improved, a deceitful heart narrowly to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, many graces to be exerciſed, many corruptions to be mortified, many enemies to be vanquiſhed &amp;c. Here's <hi>work,</hi> here is <hi>much work,</hi> here's <hi>hard work (Heaven work is hard work)</hi> here's <hi>work</hi> wherein a man muſt be ſomewhat <hi>curious</hi> and <hi>exact,</hi> Phil. 2.12. <hi>Work out your ſalvation, &amp;c. Worke,</hi> and <hi>work it out,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Homil. <hi>8.</hi> in cap. <hi>2.</hi> ad Philip. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> extremas ſummaſque vires velut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonizantes exerite. <hi>Corn. A Lap.</hi>
               </note> (that is) with much <hi>accurateneſſe</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> expounds it.) The whole life of a Chriſtian is like walking in a journey, nay, 'tis not a bare <hi>walking,</hi> but a <hi>ſtriving,</hi> Matth. 7.24. 'tis not a bare <hi>walking,</hi> but a <hi>walking up the Hill;</hi> (for ſo your way to Heaven lies) nay, 'tis a <hi>running,</hi> nay, tis like the <hi>running of a race,</hi> 1 Cor. 9 24. Hebrews 12.1. nay, higheſt of all, tis ſet forth by the <hi>ultimus conatus,</hi> or <hi>impetus</hi> in the running of a race,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> pergit in Tranſlatione à curſoribus ſumptâ; qui ſi quando ſummo &amp; quaſi jam ultimo impetu nitantur, prono &amp; quaſi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sipiti corpore feruntur ad ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum. <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14. <hi>reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before.</hi> A Metaphor taken from Horſes or Men, who in their running, when they come near the <hi>goal,</hi> or <hi>meta,</hi> they ſtretch forth themſelves, and ſo put forth their utmoſt might. All this ſets before us the <hi>laboriouſneſſe,</hi> and painfulneſſe of a Chriſtians life. This is the firſt thing which is held out in the metaphor of the Text; The Spirit of God in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151189:9"/>Scripture delighting thus to expreſſe ſpiritual activity and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, as <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. <hi>As ye have received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walk ye in him;</hi> and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.25. <hi>If we live in the Spirit, let us walk in the Spirit;</hi> (h. e.) if you have truly received Chriſt by faith, and have really a life from, and in the Spirit; then walk, and be active, and active according to what you profeſſe is wrought in you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a Chriſtians life is a <hi>walking:</hi> His life is a <hi>progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive life. Walking,</hi> 'tis <hi>motus progreſſivus.</hi> A childe of God is ſaid to <hi>walk,</hi> becauſe he goes forward in Heavens way; every action in his life is as a ſtep, a pace, by which he gets nearer to his <hi>fathers houſe.</hi> Every day <hi>ſin</hi> is more <hi>weak</hi> (like the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi>) <hi>Grace</hi> more <hi>ſtrong</hi> (like the houſe of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) <hi>affections</hi> more <hi>ſpiritual, duties</hi> more <hi>holy, love</hi> more <hi>pure, prayer</hi> more <hi>fervent,</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> more <hi>humbled.</hi> Thus gracious ſouls do <hi>walk,</hi> becauſe they go from <hi>faith to faith,</hi> Rom. 1.17. from <hi>ſtrength to ſtrength,</hi> Pſalm 84.7. <hi>Hee that hath cleane hands ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, chap.</hi> 17.9. And ſaith <hi>Solomon, The path of the juſt is as the ſhining light, that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day,</hi> Prov. 4.18. 'tis not perfectly light as ſoon as 'tis day; light comes in <hi>pedetentim,</hi> and by degrees. The Chriſtian is not perfect upon his Converſion, but he growes on towards perfection, alwaies filling up <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that which is <hi>lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his faith,</hi> 1 Theſ. 3.10. <hi>perfecting holineſſe in the feare of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.1. by all Ordinances, by all Providences, growing till he come to the <hi>meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4.13. and there be ſtops, and walks no further, for that is his <hi>Non-ultra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, A Chriſtians life is a <hi>walking.</hi> His life is a <hi>regular and ordered life. Walking,</hi> 'tis <hi>motus ordinatus &amp; diſpoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus.</hi> 'Tis not a confuſed, but a regulated, and ordered motion. Such is the life of every true Chriſtian; he is none of thoſe that live at <hi>randome,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in a <hi>diſorderly</hi> manner, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.11. His converſation is an <hi>ordered converſation.</hi> Pſalm 50.23. <hi>To him that ordereth his Converſation aright, will I ſhew the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Gods.</hi> He is one that meaſures and ſquares every thing by the Line and Plummet. Hee walks <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>exactly.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151189:9"/>Epheſ.</hi> 5.15. By the <hi>rule</hi> of the <hi>new creature,</hi> Gal. 6.16. And what is this <hi>rule? The Word,</hi> the <hi>ſure,</hi> and <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>infallible Word;</hi> this is the <hi>Compaſſe</hi> by which he <hi>ſteers,</hi> the <hi>Starre</hi> by which he <hi>ſails.</hi> In matters of <hi>faith,</hi> in matters of <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, in credendis, in agendis,</hi> ſtill to the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> Iſai. 8.20. What ſaith the Word? Is ſuch a ſin there prohibited? I muſt not meddle with it: Is ſuch a Duty there enjoyned? be it never ſo contrary to fleſh and blood, I muſt not balk it; and ſo in every particular moral act. I may call a true Chriſtian, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Word, or a living Decalogue. The Word is <hi>written</hi> in his heart, 'tis <hi>held forth</hi> in his life. Phil. 2.16. <hi>Holding forth the Word of life.</hi> He doth not only lay up the Word of life in hearing, but he doth hold forth the Word of life, in ſquaring all his actions to it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, A Chriſtians life is a <hi>walking.</hi> His obedience is free and ingenuous. <hi>Walking,</hi> 'tis <hi>mot us ſpontaneus &amp; voluntarius.</hi> The truly regenerate Chriſtian, whatever he doth in the ſervice of God, he doth it freely, not by force and compulſion, or a baſe mercenary ſpirit, but from an <hi>inward principle</hi> of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>love.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.14. <hi>The love of God conſtraineth us. Oh bleſſed conſtraint!</hi> ſweet is the violence of love. <hi>Amor meus, pondus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; eo feror quocunque feror,</hi> Auguſt. Love is the golden weight that hangs upon the gracious ſoul, and this makes every wheel in it to move, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. <hi>Thy people ſhall be a willing people in the day of thy power;</hi> in the Hebrew 'tis in the Abſtract, <hi>willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> Chriſts people are very willing in their whole compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the will of God. <hi>Xenocrates</hi> being asked, What he could do more for his Scholars then others did for theirs? made this anſwer, This I can do, ſaith he, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t id voluntate faciant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serv in Virg. Aeneid. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod alii jure coguntur. My Scholars ſhall do that willingly, which others ſhall do only by compulſion.</hi> This is truly applicable to Chriſt; he makes his people a <hi>willing people<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they are all Voluntiers in his ſervice; 'tis not becauſe they ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ot help it; no 'tis their <hi>choice, their delight,</hi> Pſal. 40.8. 'tis not their neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but their option, Pſal. 119.30. <hi>I have choſen the way of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, A Chriſtians life is a walking, his obedience is <hi>even</hi> and <hi>uniform.</hi> Walking, 'tis <hi>motus aequabilis,</hi> 'tis not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151189:10"/>a motion by girds and ſtarts, but an equal, uniforme moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thus the child of God may be ſaid to <hi>walk,</hi> hee is one that holds on with an even foot, with an equall and conſtant pace, in the way of holineſſe, Pſalm 119.112. <hi>I have enclined my heart to perform thy ſtatutes alway, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end.</hi> Mark theſe two expreſſions, <hi>alway,</hi> and <hi>even unto the end.</hi> The hypocrite runs faſt at firſt, but 'tis too ſwift to hold long, and therefore he gives out in a little time.<note place="margin">Job 27.10</note> His Religion is ſoon out of breath. <hi>Will he alwayes call upon God?</hi> The <hi>young man</hi> makes much haſte to Chriſt, but it laſts not. He runs away as faſt from him, as ever he runned to him.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.4</note> Some mens <hi>goodneſſe is but as the morning cloud, and as the early dew, which is ſoon gone away.</hi> Here lies the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the upright Chriſtian, he is one that holds out, he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veres with an even tread, till he come to glory: where you had him ſome years ago, there you have him ſtill, alwayes preſſing after perfection, but never changing ſo as to leave the good ways of God. 'Tis <hi>Cajetans</hi> obſervation here upon <hi>Enoch:</hi> 'tis twice ſaid of him,<note place="margin">Bis de Enoch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur (&amp; ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lavit cum Deo) ad explicandum quod ab ineunte aetate profecit in viâ Dei, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveravit profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendo in eâdem ſemper. <hi>Cajet.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He walked with God,</hi> ver. 22. and ver. 24. To hold forth this; (ſaith he) He <hi>began</hi> at firſt ſo to walk with God, and he continued to the end in that walking with God.</p>
            <p>I have ſhewn you in what reſpects a Chriſtians life may be ſaid to be a Walk. I now come to ſhew you in what reſpects it may be ſaid to be a <hi>Walk with God.</hi> And that I ſhall alſo do in five things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, A Chriſtian Life is a <hi>Walk with God,</hi> becauſe he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes walks <hi>as in the preſence of God.</hi> To <hi>walk with God,</hi> is as much as to <hi>walk before God.</hi> This was Gods charge to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1</note> 
               <hi>I am God All-ſufficient, walk before me and be thou perfect.</hi> This was <hi>Abrahams</hi> practice; <hi>The Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> walk,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 24.40</note> 
               <hi>will ſend his Angels with thee, &amp;c.</hi> This was <hi>Davids</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſolution, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.9. <hi>I will walk before the Lord in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the living;</hi> in the Hebrew 'tis, <hi>before the face of the Lord.</hi> The real Saint lives as in the ſight of God, doth all as in the ſight of God, thinks as in the ſight of God, trades as in the ſight of God, prayes as in the ſight of God, walks when he is moſt private, as in the ſight of God. As
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151189:10"/>the Apoſtles in the execution of their <hi>miniſterial Function, they</hi> did all <hi>as in the ſight of God;</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17. He hopes to ſee God hereafter, he knowes God ſees him here,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>intimè patientia.</hi> Vid. Metaph. Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catam in Beza in loc.</note> and he doth all as knowing there is an All-ſeeing eye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him (that is) a God to <hi>obſerve</hi> him, who is <hi>totus oculus,</hi> (as the Father calls him) <hi>in whoſe ſight every creature is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, all things being naked and opened unto him,</hi> Hebrewes 4.13.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, A Chriſtians life is a <hi>walking with God,</hi> in reſpect of that <hi>fellowſhip</hi> and <hi>converſe</hi> that he hath <hi>with God.</hi> Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a poſture of converſe. When two walk together, there is a familiar intercourſe, a mutual breathing out of love betwixt them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.14. <hi>We took ſweet counſel together, and walked unto the houſe of God in company.</hi> Thus 'tis with God and the believing ſoul, there is not a bare reconciliation betwixt them (though that there muſt be too, for, <hi>Can two walk to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unleſſe they be agreed?</hi> Amos 3.3.) but a friendly, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, reciprocal converſe. God converſes with the believers. <hi>He ſpake to Moſes, as a man ſpeaks to his friend,</hi> Exodus 33.11. <hi>Abraham was the friend of God,</hi> Iſai. 41.8. Jam. 2.23. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him,</hi> Pſal. 25.14. Prov. 3.33. what converſe more intimate, and carries more of friendſhip, then the <hi>imparting of ſecrets,</hi> John 15.15. Chriſt promiſes <hi>to come</hi> to ſuch, and to <hi>ſup with them,</hi> Rev. 3.21. <hi>John</hi> lay in his boſome. 'Tis a gracious Promiſe, that, <hi>John</hi> 14.23. <hi>My Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him;</hi> Abode! for what? ſurely for ſoul-raviſhing communion. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, <hi>Believers converſe</hi> with God. <hi>Truly our fellowſhip is with the Father and the Son.</hi> 1 John 1.3. This is better felt then expreſt. To the people of God, holy Ordinances are as ſo many <hi>Fields</hi> and <hi>Galleries,</hi> wherein they walk with God. How do they in prayer unboſome themſelves to God! Here are ſecret ſins, wilt thou not ſubdue them? here are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret doubts, wilt thou not reſolve them? here are ſecret wants, wilt thou not ſupply them? when they cannot go to a friend on earth, they can go to God their friend in Heaven, and tell him their concernments, where 'tis well, where 'tis ill, what
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151189:11"/>pleaſes, what pinches, and the Lord makes real returnes of love and mercy to them; they are leaſt alone, when they are moſt alone; they aw the preſence of God, and they enjoy the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God. And this is as the morning of glory, the lower room of heaven, the praelibation of the future joy, the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sabbath <hi>per Prolepſin</hi> (as ſome would have our Sabbath to be,<note place="margin">Vid. Gom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. de Orig Sabb.</note> in the inſtitution of it, <hi>before the fall of man,</hi> Gen. 2.3.)</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, A Chriſtians life is a <hi>walking with God,</hi> becauſe his life is a <hi>raiſed, ſpiritual, heavenly life. He walks with God, becauſe he lives above this world;</hi> this <hi>vain world,</hi> this <hi>deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful world,</hi> this <hi>troubleſome world,</hi> this <hi>defiling world.</hi> I do not wrong it, it deſerves all theſe Epithetes. 'Tis a <hi>vain world,</hi> vain in point of duration, <hi>it paſſes away,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.31. vaine in point of <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> it cannot fill and ſatisfie an immortal ſoul, the banks are too big to be filled up with a few drops.<note place="margin">Iſai. 28.20</note> 
               <hi>The bed is too ſhort, and the covering is too narrow;</hi> a Gyant cannot lye upon it. <hi>As nothing but Chriſt could ſatisfie God, ſo nothing but Chriſt can ſatisfie the ſoul. In the fulneſſe of this ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency they ſhall be in ſtraits,</hi> Job 20.22. <hi>Solomon</hi> had as much of worldly enjoyments, as ever any had, and was as able to paſſe a right judgement upon them; and he tells us, <hi>The eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, nor the eare with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.8. No, <hi>Vanity of vanities, all is vanity,</hi> verſ. 14.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo a <hi>deceitful</hi> world; it promiſes much, it performes but little.<note place="margin">Matth. 13.22 1 Cor. 7.31 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fallit. <hi>Stapul.</hi>
               </note> God out-does his Promiſes the world is ſhort of its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, there's leſſe in the performance then there was in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: 'tis the beſt when we have it not; for 'tis big in hope, little in hand; 'tis like <hi>Sodoms Apples,</hi> beautiful to the eye at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but when you touch them, they crumble to aſhes. The miſtaken Traveller, when he is in the valley, and ſees the high Hill, he thinks it touches the very skye, and if he was but at the top of it, he ſhould be able alſo to touch it with his little finger, but (alas) when he comes there, he's as far from the Heavens, as he was in the valley. Many in a low conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if they might be thus and thus, ſo noble, ſo rich, <hi>Sublimi feriam,</hi> &amp;c. Oh, how contented ſhould they be! God lets
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151189:11"/>them have that which they did deſire, and they are as farre from what they promiſed to themſelves, as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>'Tis a <hi>troubleſome world;</hi> 'Its <hi>gall</hi> is more then its <hi>honey: it pierces men through with many ſorrows;</hi> 'tis not only <hi>vanity,</hi> but <hi>vexation:</hi> have <hi>all,</hi> 'tis but <hi>vanity;</hi> want but a <hi>little,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10.</note> 'tis <hi>vexation. Ahab</hi> is ſick becauſe he hath not poor <hi>Naboths vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. Haman</hi> wants but a knee from <hi>Mordecai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 21.4 Eſth. 3.5.</note> and this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitters all.</p>
            <p>Nay, Laſtly, (which is worſt of all) 'tis a <hi>defiling world;</hi> It does but little good to the body, and much hurt to the ſoul. 'Tis <hi>the root of all evil:</hi> you cannot tell your mony,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Tim. 6.10.</hi> Beatus qui poſt illa non abiit, quae poſſeſſa o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant, amata inquinant, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa cruciant. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> but there's a filth, a ſoil left upon the fingers; <hi>The great defiling, is the heart-defiling;</hi> if the world be there, it certainly defiles it with <hi>vile affections, ſinful luſts, exceſſes in carnal delights.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Chriſt that loves to dwel in a pure heart, when the world comes in, he goes out.</p>
            <p>Now (I ſay) a child of God <hi>walks with God,</hi> becauſe he <hi>lives above this world.</hi> He is <hi>crucified</hi> to it, and it is crucified to him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14. It ſees but little in him, and he ſees as little in it: and therefore the <hi>Christian</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> are <hi>well-met,</hi> for they ſcorn each other; he is <hi>dead</hi> to theſe ſublunary things, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. he doth not ſo much as <hi>look</hi> at them, (fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then as they are <hi>neceſſary ſupports, fruits of love, engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to duty, objects of lawful care and joy,</hi> and ladders by which a man may aſcend to God, 2 Cor 4.18. He keeps them all <hi>under his feet,</hi> Rev. 12.1. (that's right <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>heart,</hi> the <hi>world</hi> under the <hi>feet;</hi> not the <hi>world</hi> in the <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the feet; not laying Chriſt in the <hi>manger,</hi> and the world in the beſt <hi>room;</hi>) all are to him but as a ſhadow, a kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw, a pageant, I comical ſhew, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. and therefore <hi>he joyes as though he joyed not, weeps as though he wept not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>uſes the world as not uſing it,</hi> doth all to it with a careleſſe hand, but ſerves God with all his <hi>might.</hi> I might here much enlarge. Take the man I am ſpeaking of, ſee what a raiſed, elevated life he lives. The judgment of the world doth not trouble him, the frowns of the world do not ſink him, the ſmiles of the world do not flatter him, the cares of the world do not burden him, the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151189:12"/>ſnares of the world do not entangle him, the <hi>pleaſures</hi> of the world do not <hi>bewitch</hi> him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pil. 3.20. Matth. 6.21</hi> Omnia praeter Christum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genti laborant parvitate. <hi>Nieremb.</hi>
               </note> In ſhort, <hi>His converſation is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> his <hi>life</hi> is where his <hi>heart</hi> is, and his <hi>heart</hi> is where his <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> is; as to <hi>earth, perſons,</hi> and <hi>things,</hi> all but <hi>loſs,</hi> but <hi>dung</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. Thus he <hi>lives above the world,</hi> even whiles he <hi>lives in the world;</hi> and this is <hi>to walke with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, a Chriſtians life is <hi>a walk with God,</hi> for he is one that duly obſerves God in all the diſcoveries which he makes of himſelf. <hi>Enoch walked with God,</hi> he took notice of God, and made due obſervation of him. So that as the Chriſtian walks with God <hi>in Gods obſerving of him,</hi> ſo he walks with God <hi>in his obſerving of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To open this, you may know that God hath made a fourfold diſcovery of himſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the <hi>Light of nature,</hi> that <hi>inbred light,</hi> which every man brings into the world with him. All ſaving knowledg of God was loſt in <hi>Adams fall,</hi> but there is a general knowledg of God,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.18.</note> (that <hi>he is,</hi> that he is <hi>thus and thus</hi>) which is engraven in every man, upon the Law of his being, for though he hath quite loſt his <hi>Grace,</hi> yet he hath not quite loſt his <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Take him <hi>in puris naturalibus,</hi> he is not <hi>raſa Tabula,</hi> a meer <hi>vacuum,</hi> a white-ſheet of paper, wherein nothing is written; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet remains, both in <hi>matters of knowledge,</hi> and in <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of practice;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vera eſt ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, nibil eſt in intellectu, quin prius fuerit in ſenſu, tametſi quaedam noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae naſcuntur nobiſcum, quas vocant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anct. vol. 4. in diſp.</hi> Non eſt muta rerum Natura, ſed undique lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quax. <hi>Eraſm.</hi>
               </note> hee hath ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in matters of <hi>knowledg,</hi> and a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Rom. 2.15. in <hi>matters of practice,</hi> and to theſe things he is not <hi>institutus,</hi> but <hi>natus,</hi> not <hi>doctus,</hi> but <hi>factus,</hi> (as the Orator ſpeaks) if there were no Scriptures to reveal them, there is ſomething <hi>innate</hi> with him, that would command his <hi>aſſent</hi> to them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God hath diſcovered himſelf in his <hi>glorious works,</hi> both of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Providence:</hi> the whole Creation is a ſilent <hi>Preacher</hi> of God, <hi>verbum viſibile</hi> (as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeaks of the Sacrament) <hi>The Heavens declare the glory of the Lord, and the Firmament ſheweth his handy worke,</hi> Pſal. 19.1. There is in the very <hi>volume</hi> of the <hi>Creatures,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Rom. 1.20, <hi>For the inviſible things of him from the Creation of the world, are clearly ſeen,</hi> (how?) <hi>being understood by the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151189:12"/>things that are made</hi> (what are thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>?) <hi>even his eternal Power and God-head.</hi> The world is nothing but <hi>mundi ſtatua</hi> (as the Platoniſts call it) 'tis Gods <hi>great Library,</hi> as <hi>Baſil</hi> calls it; 'tis the firſt Bible that God made, <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> 'Tis nothing but <hi>God manifested</hi> and <hi>drawn out,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſus mundus nibil aliud eſt quàm Deus explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. <hi>Cuſan. Savonar. Tri. Cr. l. 1. c 1.</hi> Qui fecit mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum creando, facit mundum quotidiè regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. <hi>Zanch.</hi> Qui curat An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos in coelo, curat vermicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los in coeno. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> as the Cardinal <hi>Cuſanus</hi> phraſeth it; All the creatures are but as a ladder, by which we may aſcend to God, which whileſt the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is fixt upon, <hi>in Dei notionem quedammodo manuduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; ſublimatur.</hi> And ſo look upon the <hi>works of Providence,</hi> there ſomething may be ſeen of God. <hi>Non fecit &amp; abiit, dixit Philoſophus, &amp; rectè</hi> (ſayes <hi>Luther</hi>). God did not make the world, and then leave it. No, he works ſtill, <hi>John</hi> 5.17. <hi>My Father worketh hitherto.</hi> There is a <hi>wiſe, governing, upholding Providence,</hi> which doth reach to every <hi>creature,</hi> from the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gel</hi> on the <hi>Throne,</hi> to the worm upon the dung-hill. Let a man ſtudy the Book of Providence, (eſpecially in the myſteries and deep parts of it (for there are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Word of God</hi>) he muſt acknowledg a God, and this God to be wiſe, powerful, and good.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, God hath <hi>diſcovered</hi> himſelf in his <hi>Word,</hi> and here he's <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>awn at length</hi> (if I may ſo expreſſe it with reverence.) Here you have him in a fuller, clearer character, then in either of the former. That which you have there to be gheſt at, is here plainly laid down. <hi>There</hi> you have <hi>work</hi> for <hi>Reaſon, here</hi> for <hi>Faith;</hi> there you muſt read with <hi>Spectacles,</hi> here the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt eye may ſee God very legibly ſet before it; there you have this, <hi>There is a God,</hi> &amp;c. but here you have more, <hi>This God is one in three, and three in one,</hi> a <hi>holy</hi> God, a <hi>juſt</hi> God, a God that <hi>redeem'd</hi> the world by his Son, &amp;c. No light but Scripture light can diſcover this.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, God hath <hi>diſcovered</hi> himſelf in his <hi>Son,</hi> and this is the <hi>higheſt diſcovery</hi> of all:<note place="margin">John 1.18.</note> we know moſt of God in Jeſus Chriſt, and therefore he's called <hi>ſpeculum patris,</hi> John 14.9. <hi>He that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the Father alſo; The brightneſſe of his Fathers glory,</hi> Heb. 1.3. <hi>The very image of God,</hi> Col. 1.15. <hi>And the glory of God is ſaid to ſhine forth in the face of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> as the glory of a man appeares more in his <hi>face,</hi> then it doth in all his <hi>body.</hi> You will excuſe this <hi>dig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151189:13"/>if it be ſo; but 'tis all to my preſent buſineſſe. In all theſe <hi>diſcoveries</hi> the good Chriſtian <hi>obſerves</hi> God, and takes notice of him, and he doth this too duely, or in a right manner. How's that? He obſerves him <hi>affectionately,</hi> ſo as to love him; <hi>fiducially,</hi> ſo as to truſt him; <hi>humbly,</hi> ſo as to admire him; <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically,</hi> ſo as to acknowledg him. 1. By <hi>fetching</hi> all from him. 2. By <hi>aſcribing</hi> all to him.<note place="margin">Prov. 3.6.</note> 3. By <hi>enjoying</hi> all in him. 4. By <hi>improving</hi> all for him. This is rightly to <hi>obſerve</hi> God, to know him ſo as to <hi>glorifie him as God,</hi> and this every regenerate man doth.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, (to ſhut up all with that which is <hi>general and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive.</hi>) A Chriſtians life is a <hi>walking with God,</hi> his life is a holy life. This was <hi>Enochs walking with God:</hi> Hee was a<note n="*" place="margin">Cum hîc Scriptura ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulariter de Henoch dicat. — existimant aliqui Henoch ſanctiorem quandam atque eximiam &amp; perfectiſſimam prae caetcris vitam instituiſſe, &amp;c. <hi>Malv.</hi>
               </note> holy man. Holineſſe is a walk with God, for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is the very <hi>way</hi> of God himſelf, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that walks in this way, <hi>walks with God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he walks in Gods own wya, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.3. <hi>They alſo do no iniquity, they walk in his wayes.</hi> The good man walks with God, becauſe he walks after God (as the phraſe is) <hi>Deuter.</hi> 13.4. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the<note n="(m)" place="margin">Summa eſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio imitari quem colis. <hi>Lactant.</hi>
               </note> Example of God, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, he is a <hi>God-like man,</hi> one that doth not walk <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>man,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.3. but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>God himſelf doth walk</hi> (alwayes underſtand it <hi>pro modulo</hi>). His life is a bleſſed conformity to God himſelf, in his <hi>Nature,</hi> in his <hi>Will,</hi> in his <hi>Works;</hi> he hates that which God hates, loves that which God loves, doth that which God doth, this is <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> and this is the <hi>higheſt walking with God.</hi> The learned Interpreters do generally explain <hi>Enochs Walk</hi> by this notion.<note place="margin">Piè &amp; incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patè vixit. <hi>Vatab.</hi> Hoc dictum propter ejus ſingularem ſanctitatem. <hi>Bonfrer.</hi> Ex Dei praeſcripto vitam instituit mores conformavit. <hi>Malvend.</hi> Ambulavit in timore Dei. <hi>Oncel.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>I have diſpatched the Doctrinal part, or the opening of the <hi>phraſe.</hi> I now come to <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us try our ſelves by this, whether we be Chriſtians of a <hi>right ſtamp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> this is an excellent glaſs for us to ſee our faces
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151189:13"/>in: if we weigh many Profeſſors in this balance, they will be found to be, not only light (for alas, the beſt I fear are ſo much is wanting as to meaſures and degrees, even in them,) but falſe and adulterate coin. Moſt mens religion is nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not <hi>walk</hi> with God; they are but <hi>nominal</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>Christiani ſine Christo,</hi> (as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſpeaks). I beſeech you come to the <hi>Teſt, ad ſcrutinium,</hi> try what you are, finde out your ſtate, what you are towards God, and for another world. Are we true Chriſtians, or only notional Chriſtians? How ſhall we find it out? By this, <hi>Do you walk with God?</hi> Let me tel you two things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, there are but few <hi>Enochs,</hi> few that walk with God, here and there one in a family, two or three in a pariſh,<note place="margin">Jer. 3.14.</note> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the men of the multitude they go another way. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> was a man of <hi>another ſpirit,</hi> a rare and choice ſpirit, a man by <hi>himſelf</hi> almoſt, as God ſpeaks of <hi>Caleb, Numb.</hi> 14.24. <hi>But my ſervant Caleb, becauſe he had another ſpirit with him, and hath followed me fully.</hi> Indeed all men do <hi>walk,</hi> but how? <hi>after the fleſh,</hi> Rom. 8.1. <hi>in the wayes of their own hearts,</hi> Eccleſ. 11.9. <hi>after their own devices,</hi> Jer. 18.2. <hi>after vanity,</hi> Jer. 2.5. <hi>after their own ungodly lusts,</hi> Jude 18. This is far from walking with God, and yet this is the courſe of the moſt in the world: the unclean man walks with his luſts, the covetous man with his wealth, the voluptuous man with his pleaſures, the hypocrite with his formal duties, &amp;c. Alas, with ſorrow we may ſpeak it, there are but very few that <hi>walk</hi> with God, <hi>vix tot quot Thebarum portae, &amp;c.</hi> This path of holineſs is an <hi>untrodden, unfrequented path</hi> by the generality of men. Try your ſelves therefore where you walk, whether with the <hi>moſt,</hi> or with the <hi>beſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 7.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, know this; every man is in the ſight and judgment of God <hi>according to his walking.</hi> 'Tis not <hi>Jacobs</hi> voice, that makes a true Chriſtian, a little religious talking, a parcel of fine words; God looks to the <hi>ways,</hi> not to the <hi>words;</hi> to the <hi>walking,</hi> not to the <hi>talking.</hi> Nor 'tis not ſome particular <hi>acts,</hi> that ſet a man right and ſtraight, as to his ſpiritual condition. One <hi>Swallow</hi> doth not make a <hi>Spring;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na Hirundo non facit ver.</note> ſome few good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do not make a Chriſtian. <hi>Wicked men in ſome particular
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151189:14"/>acts may be very good. Cain</hi> ſacrifices, <hi>Ahab</hi> humbles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Jehu</hi> is zealous;<note place="margin">Gen. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 King. 21.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Kings 10.16.</note> like the Dial, which though it ſtands, yet at ſome particular time once in the ſpace of twelve hours it will be right. And on the other hand, <hi>A child of God in ſome particular acts may be very bad. Noah</hi> is drunk, <hi>David</hi> unclean,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.21. 2 Sam. 11.4 Matth. 26.74 Pſal. 73.15.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> denies his Maſter; &amp;c. therefore no man is to <hi>judg</hi> by theſe, for then he will <hi>justifie</hi> the wicked, and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn</hi> the righteous; but look to your <hi>walking,</hi> the general <hi>bent</hi> and <hi>tendency</hi> of the <hi>heart,</hi> the <hi>ſcope</hi> and <hi>courſe</hi> of your <hi>converſation;</hi> whatever this is, according to that God judges of you, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. <hi>I ſleep, but my heart waketh.</hi> Sometimes I turn aſide for a pace or two, but the great inclination of my heart, is to keep cloſe to God. Here's <hi>grace,</hi> ſo God eſteems it. The ſum of all is this; you <hi>pray</hi> ſometimes, and <hi>hear</hi> the Word, and do good things; but is your <hi>walk</hi> with God, that the bias of the ſoul ſtands towards God, the <hi>impetus</hi> of your ſpirits is after him, that there is an <hi>habitual work</hi> within you, which turns the great ſtream of the heart towards holineſſe? if ſo, you are <hi>Enoch's, real Saints:</hi> be of good comfort, <hi>your glory is ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The main uſe ſhall be by way of <hi>Exhortation,</hi> to preſſe this upon you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</note> that you live this excellent life of <hi>walking</hi> with God. Oh that I might prevail with ſome, to reſolve in the ſtrength of God, to ſet upon this <hi>walking.</hi> This concerns us all: We that are <hi>Ministers,</hi> let us <hi>walk</hi> with God; as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Levi, He walked with God in peace and equity, and did turn many a way from iniquity,</hi> Malachi 2 6. You that are private Chriſtians, whether rich or poor, high or low, do you <hi>walk</hi> with God? Great perſons will not let mean men walk with them, that's a poſture of too much familiarity; but God is willing the meaneſt creature ſhould <hi>walk</hi> with him, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with him.</p>
            <p>In the proſecuting of this verſe, I'le do two things. 1. <hi>I'le lay down ſome directions.</hi> 2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rge the duty upon you by ſome Motives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Directive part, I'le ſpeak 1. To the <hi>matter</hi> of your <hi>walking.</hi> 2. To the <hi>manner</hi> of your <hi>walking.</hi> For the <hi>matter</hi> of your walking, I'le briefly run over the particulars which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151189:14"/>have been mentioned, and preſſe each upon you; <hi>Walk</hi> and <hi>walk with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>Walk</hi> and be active Chriſtians. The Apoſtle exhorts <hi>Timothy,</hi> to <hi>ſtir up the gift of God which was in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eſt ignem cine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus conditum folle aut flatu ſuſcitare, ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardeſcat. <hi>Corn. A Lap. Cant. 1.12 Matth. 5.15</hi>
               </note> 2 Tim. 1.6. I would preſſe the ſame upon you. Have you <hi>grace?</hi> ſtir it up, put it out into act, let your <hi>spikenard</hi> ſend forth its <hi>ſmell,</hi> let not your light be concealed under a buſhel. Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is active in the wicked, Grace ſhould be active in the good; ſhall they do more to diſhonour God, then you to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him? you have your grace for action, firſt for<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 7.12</hi> Paulum ſepultae distat inertiae celata virtus. <hi>Hor.</hi> De non entibus &amp; de non ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parentibus ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſt ratio.</note> 
               <hi>fruit,</hi> then for glory. As good <hi>no</hi> grace, as not to act it. The way to have more, is to act what you have, <hi>Habenti dabitur,</hi> Matth. 13.12 The <hi>active</hi> Chriſtian is the moſt <hi>excellent</hi> Chriſtian. In fowls that go, the leg is beſt; in fowls that fly, the wing is beſt; the exerciſe of the part makes the difference. If you be <hi>idle,</hi> God will loſe his <hi>glory;</hi> for as to men here, his glory depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the acting of grace, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine, &amp;c. The habit of grace brings glory to us, but 'tis the acting of grace that brings glory to God.</hi> Your <hi>Saviour acts</hi> his <hi>grace</hi> for you, do you <hi>act</hi> your <hi>grace</hi> for him; he is alwayes at work for you: the Heavens are alwayes in motion,<note place="margin">John 5.17</note> but the Earth ſtands ſtill. Chriſt ever lives for us, we ſeldome live for him,<note place="margin">Heb 7.25.</note> the greater is our ſhame. Well, <hi>up</hi> and <hi>be doing,</hi> and the Lord will be with you; your <hi>time</hi> is but <hi>ſhort,</hi> your <hi>work</hi> is <hi>great, double your diligence,</hi> and be very <hi>active.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Walk</hi> and be <hi>growing</hi> Chriſtians, 2 Pet. 3. ult. <hi>Grow in Grace, and in the knowledg, &amp;c.</hi> Be like <hi>Ezekiels</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which were firſt to the <hi>ankles,</hi> then to the <hi>knees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 47.3, 4, 5</note> then to the <hi>loins,</hi> afterwards they were a <hi>river</hi> that no man could paſſe over: Thus do you riſe and increaſe in Grace, go from <hi>little to much,</hi> from <hi>ſincerity</hi> to <hi>perfection;</hi> let grace have its <hi>perfect work;</hi> whileſt others are joyning houſe to houſe,<note place="margin">Jam. 1 4 Iſai. 5.8</note> grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in wealth, do you <hi>grow in grace;</hi> you cannot have too much of it: a man may have too much of the world, he cannot have too much of <hi>grace:</hi> wicked men grow <hi>worſe</hi> and <hi>worſe,</hi> do you <hi>grow better</hi> and <hi>better;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.13</note> your opportunities are admirable; if you ſtand ſtill, who ſhall go forward? We have many in theſe times, who are like the Sun in <hi>Joſhuah</hi>'s time, that <hi>ſtood ſtill;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 10.12</note>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151189:15"/>many worſe, like the Sun in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> time, they are gone backwards many degrees:<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.8</note> O Chriſtians, take heed of this, and on the other hand make ſome progreſſe in the things of God; from <hi>babes</hi> in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.13, 24</note> be <hi>ſtrong</hi> men in Chriſt; from thoſe that muſt be <hi>fed with milk, get your ſenſes exerciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d;</hi> from <hi>dwarfs</hi> be like the <hi>ſons of Anak,</hi> in <hi>faith and holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Walk,</hi> and be <hi>orderly Christians,</hi> keep to the <hi>rule</hi> in every thing be not Antinomians in practice: Our <hi>doctrinal An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomians</hi> are not <hi>many,</hi> our <hi>practical Antinomians</hi> are very <hi>many;</hi> they <hi>dispute,</hi> and we <hi>practice;</hi> our <hi>heads</hi> oppoſe, our <hi>lives</hi> embrace their <hi>dangerous opinion:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. ult.</note> Oh, let your <hi>converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> be an <hi>ordered converſation:</hi> An <hi>ordered Covenant</hi> calls for an <hi>ordered converſation;</hi> our <hi>Grace</hi> in <hi>duty,</hi> muſt anſwer to <hi>Gods grace in mercy.</hi> Your <hi>Covenant is ordered in all things,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.5. Let your <hi>carriage</hi> anſwer to this <hi>Covenant.</hi> Doe nothing, but be able to ſay, <hi>Here's my rule for what I doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, <hi>Walk, act from a free ſpirit,</hi> Pſalm 51.12. Let your obedience be nothing but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>labour</hi> of love:<note place="margin">Heb. 6.10.</note> act not as <hi>ſlaves,</hi> but as <hi>ſonnes;</hi> not to ſhun the <hi>rod,</hi> but to pleaſe the <hi>Father;</hi> Though Heaven and Hell ſhould be burnt up (as that famous Martyr ſaid) that there ſhould be no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to affright you, no reward to allure you, yet from an inward principle of love to the wayes of God, <hi>walk</hi> in them; look upon it as your meat and drink,<note place="margin">John 4.34</note> 
               <hi>to be doing the Will of your heavenly Father;</hi> Say, Lord, obedience is enough, a ſufficient reward to it ſelf. This ſpiritual ingenuity will be your crown and glory. Nothing commends an action (ſaith <hi>Lactantius</hi>) ſo much as this. 'Tis the will that is <hi>menſura actionum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquinas</hi>) let a man do that which is never ſo good, if he doth it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2 Aug. Confeſſ. l. 1. c. 12.</note> that ſpoils the action; for <hi>Nemo invitus bene facit, etiamſi bonum eſt quod facit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, <hi>Walk, hold on with an even pace in the good wayes of God.</hi> The <hi>even</hi> Chriſtian is the <hi>excellent</hi> Chriſtian; when the pulſe beats evenly, all is well. To be ſometimes up, and ſomes times down, ſometimes hot, ſometimes cold; this argues a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered heart: many are like your Jades, either they will
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151189:15"/>
               <hi>gallop,</hi> or <hi>ſtand</hi> ſtill; either they will be very good, or nothing at all. Oh, that we could get a fixed heart,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.7</note> to be conſtant and uniform in the whole tenor of our life! Thus I would have you <hi>walk;</hi> but farther, <hi>walk with God:</hi> that's the <hi>ſecond thing.</hi> And here,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Walks</hi> alwayes as in the <hi>Preſence of God, believe</hi> this as a truth; where-ever you are, God is with you. <hi>Sin</hi> may hinder you from his <hi>gracious preſence,</hi> but no place can <hi>ſecure</hi> you from his <hi>obſerving preſence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.7, 8, 9 10, 11, 12</note> 
               <hi>Whither ſhall I go from thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit?</hi> or, <hi>Whither ſhall I fly from thy preſence? If I aſcend up into heaven,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis with God as 'tis with a Picture: if it be well drawn, where-ever you are in the room its eye is upon you. Thus 'tis with the <hi>All-ſeeing eye of God,</hi> 'tis upon us where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are.<note place="margin">2 Kings 5.26</note> 
               <hi>Went not mine heart with thee when the man turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again from his chariot to meet thee?</hi> ſaith <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Gehazi.</hi> We think to carry things cloſely, but we are fooliſh. God is privy to our very thoughts, to our greateſt ſecrets and retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. This a child of God <hi>knows,</hi> and he would not have it otherwiſe. <hi>Velleius Paterculus</hi> tells us a ſtory of one <hi>Livi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Druſus;</hi> There comes an Artiſt to him, and tells him, if he pleaſed, he would ſo contrive his houſe, that do what he would, none ſhould ſee him; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t libera à conſpectu, immunis ab omnibus arbitriis eſſet.</hi> No, ſaith <hi>Druſus,</hi> but rather ſhew your Art, make my houſe ſo that all may ſee me, for I am not aſhamed to be ſeen. <hi>Tu verò ſiquid in te artis eſt, ita compone domum meam, ut ab omnibus conſpici poſſit.</hi> I apply it to a child of God. The Hypocrites torment is Gods Omniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency and Omnipreſency, he would fain not be ſeen by God and men; but the upright man, he knows God ſees him, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces at it. Well, you believe this, live in the practical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of it; what a world of ſin would this prevent, if men did but alwayes ſet God before them! When <hi>Latimer</hi> heard the pen behind the curtain, he anſwered very warily. The <hi>Romanes,</hi> when they would not do an undecent act, they would fancy a <hi>Cato, &amp;c.</hi> a <hi>Fabius</hi> in the room. The <hi>Maid</hi> would not gratifie the luſt of her unchaſte ſuitor, till he could find a room where God might not ſee them; and ſo ſhe eſcaped his wicked ſolicitations. <hi>Atheiſme</hi> is at the bottom of every ſin,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151189:16"/>and this is one great piece of it; we think God doth not ſee us. And therefore work this home upon your ſpirits, and whenever a temptation comes, cruſh it with this, <hi>How ſhall I do this under the eye of God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.8</note> The eye of man would keep off much ſin in the world, and ſhall not the eye of God much more? Walk thus, and you ſhall not be greatly moved.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>walk with God;</hi> let your <hi>converſe be with him:</hi> Let others pleaſe themſelves in their friends, in their creature-enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in their carnal converſes, do you delight your ſelves in <hi>God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſſueſce cum eo. <hi>Pagnin.</hi>
               </note> Let your <hi>fellowſhip be above: Acquaint thy ſelf with God. and be at yeace,</hi> Job 22.21. A man may as really by prayer and meditation, and the Promiſes, converſe with God, as one man converſes with another in a civil way. Why are you ſo much ſtrangers to it? Why ſo little with God? doth not he uſually give out that which fills the ſoul with <hi>joy unſpeakable and full of glory?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8. Pſal. 63.3</note> Are not his viſits better then life? Is not the heart ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed under the taſtes of his love? Is not the enjoyment of him infinitely above all comforts here? Is he not willing to come to you, and to give out of his Loves? Why do you not walk with him? why do you not converſe with him here, with whom it ſhall be your glory to converſe hereafter? Cry out, <hi>Whom have I in heaeven but thee?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.26 Pſal. 63.1 Pſal. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoul thirſteth for thee.</hi> Many ſay, <hi>Who wil ſhew us any good? Lord, lift' thou up the light of thy countenance upon me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Walk</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>live above this world.</hi> This is a hard duty, eſpecially to you here in this City, who have ſo much of the world; but let me prevail with you to put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practice.<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.14 Jer. 17.13 Luke 16.25 Phil. 3.19 Heb. 3.1 Tit. 2.13. 1 Cor. 3.22 Mat. 6.20. 2 Pet. 1.4 Gen. 17.1, 7</note> Let thoſe who have their <hi>portien</hi> here, whoſe <hi>names are written in the earth,</hi> who have all <hi>their good things</hi> here, let them <hi>mind earthly things,</hi> and take their <hi>fill</hi> of theſe <hi>dreggs;</hi> But you, the <hi>people of God,</hi> who have the <hi>heavenly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, great</hi> and <hi>glorious hopes, intereſt</hi> in <hi>Chriſt, treaſures</hi> in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, precious promiſes,</hi> an <hi>All ſufficient God</hi> for your <hi>God;</hi> you muſt <hi>live</hi> a <hi>higher</hi> life. If you be <hi>worldly,</hi> you <hi>debaſe God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the moſt <hi>excellent</hi> things of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> nay, your own ſelve; for that <hi>Saint</hi> which doth not <hi>live above the world, lives</hi> much <hi>beneath himſelf.</hi> The Lapwing hath a Crowne upon her head, and yet ſhe feeds upon excrements. The childe is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151189:16"/>
               <hi>heire</hi> to a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and yet he lies tumbling in the aſhes. The true <hi>believer</hi> is <hi>highly-advanced</hi> through <hi>grace;</hi> he's an <hi>heire,</hi> nay, a <hi>co-heire with Jeſus Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.17</note> for him to <hi>ſtoop</hi> to theſe <hi>beggerly enjoyments,</hi> 'tis much below him. Chriſtians, <hi>you</hi> have the <hi>Ocean,</hi> care not for the <hi>drop;</hi> the <hi>fountaine</hi> is yours,<note place="margin">Jerem. 2.13</note> away with <hi>broken ciſternes;</hi> you have the <hi>pearle,</hi> get above the <hi>dirt;</hi> (for ſo the world is, but a <hi>cabul,</hi> a <hi>dirty</hi> thing.)<note place="margin">1 Kings 9.13</note> Minde it you may, in its <hi>proper place</hi> and <hi>ſphere,</hi> keeping it under a <hi>due ſubordination;</hi> but be ſure of this, that you <hi>live above</hi> it. Let your <hi>thoughts</hi> be <hi>above</hi> it. What? from morning to night, all the day long, thinking upon this buſineſſe and that buſineſſe, this comfort, and that comfort? no room for heavenly meditation? the <hi>thoughts</hi> are the <hi>ſpirits</hi> of the ſoule (as it were), muſt all be ſpent in the worlds ſervice? The <hi>thoughts</hi> are the <hi>wings</hi> of the ſoule, will you never by them take a <hi>flight</hi> to heaven and heavenly objects? Let your <hi>love</hi> be above it.<note place="margin">Miſer eſt omnis animus vinctus amiciti â rerum mortalium-<hi>Aug. conf. l. 4. c. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world; if any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him,</hi> 1 John 2.15. Let your <hi>deſires</hi> be above it. <hi>Wilt thou ſet thine eyes upon that which is not? for riches certainly make themſelves wings, they flie away as an Eagle towards Heaven,</hi> Prov. 23.5. Let your <hi>comforts</hi> be above it, your <hi>hopes</hi> be above it, your <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> be above it; be <hi>content</hi> with the <hi>worſt</hi> of the world, be not <hi>ſatisfied</hi> with the <hi>beſt</hi> of the world: be thankful for the <hi>crumbs</hi> of the world, but do not take up with the <hi>crownes</hi> of the world. In a word, let your <hi>life</hi> be above it: <hi>Be not conformed to this world,</hi> Rom. 12.2. You live <hi>above</hi> it, when you do not live <hi>according</hi> to it; and 'tis as hard, not to live <hi>according</hi> to it, in the <hi>cuſtomes</hi> of it, as to live <hi>above</hi> it in the <hi>comforts</hi> of it. Thus I beſeech you walk with God: get your <hi>hearts looſened</hi> from all things here, and <hi>live</hi> where you muſt <hi>die;</hi> I mean, live upon that now, which, if you would have peace and comfort, you muſt live upon, when you come to die; ſay not of things, as that profane man once did of perſons, <hi>Cum iſt is mallem vivere, cum illis mallemmori;</hi> With riches I had rather live, with grace I had rather die.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>walk</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> (that is) <hi>carefully</hi> and <hi>diligently obſerve God, and inke notice of him in all the diſcoveries which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151189:17"/>he makes of himſelf.</hi> Study God in his Word, in his Works, in his Son, in every thing, and by every thing, riſe up to a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rential, humble, practical acknowledgment of God: Trace him in all his ſteps, and go as far as you can; and when you can go no further, then fall upon the admiring of him; <hi>Oh the depth of the riches; both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God! How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable are his judgments, and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> Rom. 11.33.</p>
            <p>In the Doctrinal opening of this particular, I laid down ſome practical Hints about the due obſervance of God, to which I referre you, and ſhall not here further enlarge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The laſt thing is this: <hi>walk</hi> with God by being <hi>holy:</hi> I ſay, <hi>Be holy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>as he who hath called you is holy, ſo be ye holy</hi> (and that too) <hi>in all manner of converſation;</hi> in all your relations, in every condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in your callings, at all times; in all companies, in every turn of your life,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in your whole carriage and deportment by ye <hi>holy.</hi> What Argument ſhall I uſe to enforce this advice!</p>
            <p>Be holy, for your <hi>God is</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sanctitas Dei eſt univerſalis illius juſtitia ſeu infinita, ac ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex Dei virtus qua ſeſe ut ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum bonum, omniſque boni fontem, ali áque rectae ſuae ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ac voluntati conſentanea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat &amp; diſſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea averſatur. <hi>Gomar.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>holy.</hi> Will you not be like your God? All people, whatever they pitched upon for their God, were they never ſo ignorant, they would labour to be <hi>like their god;</hi> nay, ſome would be<note n="(*)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Adulterio delectatur. quis? reſpicit Jovem, &amp;c.</hi> Vid. Jul. Firm. de er. Prof. Relig. Iſai. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>vitious,</hi> becauſe their gods were ſo. What a ſhame is it to us Chriſtians, that we are ſo unlike to our God, the <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>true God!</hi> Let us reſolve in a bleſſed imitation of God. <hi>All people will walk, every one in the name of God, and we will walk in the Name of the Lord our God for ever and ever,</hi> Micah 4.5. Be holy, for <hi>Holineſs</hi> is the very <hi>glory of God, Glorious in holineſſe,</hi> Exod. 15.11. 'Tis the <hi>glory of Chriſt. Holy, Holy, Holy, is the Lord of Hoſts:</hi> This is ſpoken of Chriſt, for ſaith <hi>John,</hi> John 12.41. <hi>Theſe things, ſaid Eſaias, when he ſaw his glory and ſpake of him</hi> (that is) <hi>of Chriſt. Holineſſe</hi> is the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> by this you do <hi>adorn the Doctrine of God our Saviour,</hi> Tit. 2.10. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is your <hi>own glory, here</hi> and <hi>hereafter.</hi> 'Tis your glory <hi>here,</hi> it puts a <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> upon you: 'Tis called, Pſal. 110.3. <hi>The Beauty of Holineſſe.</hi> 'Tis your glory <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,</hi> it certainly ends in glory. No ſeeing of God without it, Hebr. 12.14. a certainty of ſeeing God with it. They that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151189:17"/>have their <hi>fruit</hi> to <hi>holineſſe,</hi> ſhal have in <hi>the end everlasting life,</hi> Rom. 7.22.</p>
            <p>So much for the matter of your walking, I come to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing, to lay down ſome Directions concerning the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of your walking with God.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, you muſt walk <hi>humbly</hi> with God. 'Tis not <hi>thouſands</hi> of <hi>Rams,</hi> or <hi>ten thouſands</hi> of <hi>Rivers</hi> of <hi>Oyl, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are not the things that God looks for: <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>and to walk humbly with thy God? God</hi> loves the <hi>humble</hi> Walker. He <hi>Himſelf</hi> loves to walk with ſuch an one, nay, to <hi>dwell</hi> with him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. The <hi>proud</hi> man, <hi>God ſees him a far off,</hi> Pſal. 138.6. He <hi>keeps</hi> at a <hi>diſtance</hi> from him; and when he doth draw near him, 'tis not as a <hi>friend</hi> to <hi>walk</hi> with him, but as an <hi>enemy</hi> he <hi>marches</hi> againſt him in <hi>battel array,</hi> to break him in peeces, ſo the word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, <hi>God reſiſteth the proud,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ex-adverſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi aciem inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it. <hi>Gerhard.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a word hard to be opened.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye therefore clothed with humility. Humility</hi> is the great <hi>Grace. Auguſtine</hi> being ask'd what was the <hi>firſt</hi> Grace, anſwered, <hi>Humility;</hi> What's the <hi>ſecond, Humility;</hi> What the <hi>third, Humility:</hi> 'Tis all in all, 'tis a <hi>prime</hi> and <hi>choice</hi> grace, 'tis the <hi>crown,</hi> the <hi>ornament,</hi> the <hi>varniſh</hi> of every grace, 'tis that which makes eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace to thrive, nothing brings into the ſoul ſo much <hi>joy,</hi> as Humility, for God loves to lay his <hi>wines</hi> in the <hi>loweſt Cellars.</hi> Oh! labour to act this grace, and to walk humbly. What is <hi>man</hi> that he ſhould be <hi>proud?</hi> what are the beſt of men, that they ſhould be pufft up? what are you? a little <hi>duſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cum humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, cur non humilimus? <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> a little <hi>well-complexion'd</hi> duſt, poor <hi>piles</hi> of <hi>graſſe,</hi> things of nothing, <hi>finite drops,</hi> creatures, and ſinful creatures too, meditate much upon this, and upon the glorious <hi>Majeſty</hi> of God, your infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>diſtance</hi> from him, this will make you humble, this will draw out <hi>ſelf-debaſing, God exalting, grace-admiring</hi> thoughts,<note place="margin">Gen. 31.10.</note> (and there's humility) this will make you with <hi>Jacob</hi> to ſay, you are <hi>leſſe</hi> then the <hi>leaſt of all Gods mercies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 42.6. Iſaiah 6.5. Epheſ. 3.8, 1 Tim. 1.13.</note> with <hi>Job</hi> to <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor</hi> your ſelves in <hi>duſt</hi> and <hi>aſhes,</hi> with <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to cry out, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean,</hi> with <hi>Paul,</hi> the <hi>leaſt</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and the <hi>greateſt</hi> of <hi>ſinners:</hi> and this is <hi>rare</hi> walking.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, walk <hi>uprightly,</hi> be <hi>upright</hi> and <hi>ſtraight</hi> in your walking.<note place="margin">Gen. 7.1.</note> 
               <hi>I am God All-ſufficient</hi> (ſaith God to <hi>Abraham</hi>)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151189:18"/>
               <hi>walk before me, and be thou perfect,</hi> that is, <hi>upright,</hi> for <hi>ſincerity</hi> is all the <hi>perfection</hi> that here we can <hi>arrive</hi> at. He that <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth uprightly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 10.9. Eph. 6.5. Acts 2.46. 2 Chro. 6.14. Hoſ. 10.2. 1 King 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>walketh ſurely.</hi> What is it to walk uprightly? To have a <hi>ſingle</hi> heart for God, to walk with him in <hi>ſingleneſſe</hi> of heart, <hi>with all the heart,</hi> as the Scripture expreſſes it. A <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided</hi> heart is a <hi>naughty</hi> heart, when men <hi>halt</hi> betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Baal,</hi> betwixt <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth, Grace</hi> and <hi>Sin, Chriſt</hi> hath ſomething, and the <hi>Divel</hi> hath ſomething, here's hypocriſie; Take heed of this, God <hi>hates</hi> it; he can <hi>pity</hi> a <hi>child</hi> though he <hi>ſtumbles</hi> and <hi>falls,</hi> but he <hi>abhors</hi> an <hi>halting hypocrite.</hi> Let God have <hi>all,</hi> devote the whole man to him, have but<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 86.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Septuag.</hi> An hypocrite is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a double heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, James 1.8. Pſalm 101.2. Prov. 10.29. Iſa. 38.3.</note> 
               <hi>one heart,</hi> for his ſervice and glory; thus walk, and this ſhall be your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, you ſhall have much of Gods <hi>preſence, I will behave my ſelf wiſely in a perfect way, O when wilt thou come unto me?</hi> You ſhall find the <hi>influences</hi> of grace, to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> you to hold out in your walking. <hi>The way of the Lord is ſtrength to the upright.</hi> Upright walking will <hi>ſweeten</hi> every <hi>affliction.</hi> See 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1.12. will <hi>ſweeten death</hi> it ſelf to you. It did ſo to good <hi>Hezekiah, Remember, O Lord; how I have walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee in truth, and with a perfect heart:</hi> In a word, thus walk, and God will <hi>deny</hi> you <hi>nothing: The Lord will give grace and glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 84.11.</note> 
               <hi>no good thing will he withhold from them that walk uprightly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Walk</hi> with God <hi>cloſely;</hi> I might here lament the <hi>looſe</hi> walking of many Profeſſors in our age. What's become of our <hi>cloſe</hi> walking? the people of God in former times, how <hi>ſtrict</hi> were they, how <hi>circumſpect;</hi> we have found out a <hi>broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er way</hi> to Heaven, then what they walked in. We may ſadly complain, as to the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> there is a mighty forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in this <hi>Nation. Remember from whence you are fallen, and repent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſet</hi> up again <hi>cloſe walking</hi> with God, allow not your ſelves in the <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>least ſin;</hi> flee from the very <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of evil;<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>omit</hi> not any <hi>duty,</hi> be it never ſo <hi>difficult;</hi> comply with every <hi>command,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.6.</note> let no <hi>temptations</hi> cauſe you ſo much as to <hi>ſtep</hi> aſide from God; thus do you keep <hi>cloſe</hi> to God, and he will keep <hi>cloſe</hi> to you;<note place="margin">2 Chron. 15.2.</note> 
               <hi>but if you forſake him, he will forſake you.</hi> And let me tell you this, every <hi>departure</hi> from God will end in <hi>bitterneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 51.8.</note> if you <hi>leave</hi> him to gratifie <hi>corruption,</hi> look for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151189:18"/>
               <hi>broken bones.</hi> God will either make you walk <hi>cloſely</hi> or <hi>mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully;</hi> which of the two is the better, do you judge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, walk <hi>watchfully. Bleſſed is he that watcheth and keepeth his garments, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 16.15. Matth. 13. ult.</note> 
               <hi>What I ſay unto you, I ſay unto all, Watch,</hi> ſaith Chriſt. In your walking, ſee you be thus watchfull. Your <hi>way</hi> is ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, you may ſoon <hi>loſe</hi> it; the <hi>heart,</hi> like <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe,<note place="margin">Numb. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> will be <hi>flying</hi> out of the <hi>path,</hi> the <hi>Divel</hi> laies <hi>ſnares</hi> for you, many <hi>en mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> lie waiting for you, you had need look about you, and be carefull what you do, <hi>Keep thy heart with all diligence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 4.13.</note> ſaith <hi>Solomon:</hi> Keep it as a <hi>Jailor</hi> keeps his cloſe Priſoner, with a <hi>watchful eye,</hi> for fear he give him the ſlip: where ever you are, there is a <hi>deceitful heart</hi> within, a <hi>tempting Divel,</hi> and a <hi>flattering world</hi> without; look to your ſelves and <hi>keep your feet</hi> when you go into the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 5.1.</note> when you go into your own houſes: every place is full of ſnares, and therefore in all places, and <hi>in all things</hi> watch. The <hi>heeedful</hi> Walker<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is the <hi>ſure</hi> Walker. <hi>David</hi> neglecting this duty,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.5. Pſalm 73.2.</note> his <hi>feet</hi> were almoſt gone, nay, in three or four eminent caſes they were quite gone.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, <hi>walk</hi> with God <hi>unweariedly,</hi> take heed of <hi>tyring</hi> in the way of <hi>Holineſſe.</hi> The Heavenly Orbs are in perpetual <hi>motion,</hi> and yet <hi>unwearied.</hi> The Sun hath run his courſe for ſome thouſands of years, 'tis as freſh as ever it was. Oh, that <hi>Grace</hi> might imitate <hi>Nature! Be not weary in well-doing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.9. 2 Theſſ. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>you ſhal reap if ye faint not.</hi> What a ſhame is it to us? <hi>Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men</hi> are never <hi>weary</hi> in the <hi>ſervice</hi> of their <hi>luſts;</hi> and how ſoon are we weary in the <hi>ſervice</hi> of our <hi>God?</hi> We cannot ſpend a little time in prayer, but the duty grows irkſome,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.13.</note> and in the general courſe of our obedience, we are ready to ſit down almoſt as ſoon as we have ſet out. Away with this <hi>ſlothfulneſſe,</hi> hold out <hi>vigorouſly;</hi> though <hi>work</hi> be <hi>difficult,</hi> though God doth exerciſe you with much <hi>waiting,</hi> yet be not <hi>weary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, <hi>Walk</hi> with God <hi>believingly.</hi> We <hi>walk</hi> by <hi>faith,</hi> in oppoſition to ſight. Oh! that we did walk by faith in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to <hi>carnal reaſon,</hi> to <hi>ſinfull dependancies,</hi> to <hi>diſtruſtfull faintings.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.7.</note> In your <hi>reſting</hi> (I mean upon Chriſt) is the <hi>act</hi> of faith, in your <hi>walking</hi> is the <hi>life</hi> of faith. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20</note> 
               <hi>the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151189:19"/>life which he lived in the fleſh, he lived by the faith of the Son of God.</hi> The <hi>life</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> is a brave life, no life goes beyond it, but the life of <hi>fruition,</hi> and that's <hi>Heaven.</hi> Chriſtians, this life of faith ſhould be <hi>twiſted</hi> into your walking with God. That which in the Text is called <hi>walking with God, Paul</hi> calls <hi>faith</hi> (for however 'tis expreſſed in the Old Teſtament, in the New, <hi>Paul</hi> will ſet it forth by <hi>faith;</hi> for ſo <hi>excellent</hi> was this <hi>Grace</hi> in his eye, that he'l ſet the <hi>Crown</hi> of all upon the head of faith) <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5. <hi>By faith Enoch was tranſlated</hi> (that is) <hi>upon his faith:</hi> ſo then <hi>Enoch</hi> walked in <hi>faith;</hi> imitate him, I beſeech you, in this, walk in <hi>faith,</hi> or you'l never walk ſteadily: <hi>Sincerity</hi> keeps us from <hi>halting, Watchfulneſſe</hi> keeps us from <hi>ſtumbling, Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> keeps us from <hi>wandring, Reſolution</hi> keeps us from <hi>tyring,</hi> but 'tis <hi>faith</hi> that keeps us from <hi>fainting.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 27.3.</note> 
               <hi>I had fainted, but that I verily beleeved to ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord in the land of the living.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 26.3.</note> Are you <hi>weak?</hi> faith will reach you a <hi>ſtaffe,</hi> and that is God himſelf, upon whom the ſinking ſoul may <hi>ſtay</hi> it ſelf. Are you <hi>ſcorched</hi> with <hi>heat</hi> in your walking? faith wil fetch <hi>cooling</hi> vertue from the <hi>Fountain</hi> Chriſt, to refreſh you. Doth the difficulty and the tediouſneſs of the way diſcourage? See,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.26.</note> ſaith faith, <hi>There's the recompence of reward,</hi> you will be at it preſently,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>hold out.</hi> Are you afraid of enemies? faith will <hi>ſhield</hi> you. Do you <hi>want neceſſaries</hi> for your journy in your wilderneſſe-way? faith will go to Chriſt, and fetch food, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, counſel, gold &amp;c. 'twill bring in all <hi>proviſion</hi> that's ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Are you troubled becauſe you are alone? faith will bring Chriſt, the promiſes to bear you company. Are you ſometimes <hi>ſtung</hi> by the way?<note place="margin">John 3.14.</note> ſaith faith, there's the <hi>brazen Serpent</hi> to heal you. <hi>Admirable</hi> is the <hi>uſe</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>journey;</hi> make it your <hi>Vade mecum,</hi> and all is well. <hi>Faith</hi> wil do ſtrange things, 'twill lay you <hi>low,</hi> and at that ſame time 'twil <hi>lift you up;</hi> 'twill make your condition <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> by the ſame breath; <hi>bad</hi> as to <hi>weak worthleſſe</hi> ſelf; <hi>good,</hi> as to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>free</hi> grace, faith will by the <hi>ſame</hi> hand <hi>empty</hi> and <hi>fill;</hi> faith will make the <hi>Sun</hi> to <hi>ſhine,</hi> even when <hi>cloude</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe</hi> are round about you; faith will (like the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone</hi>) turn all into Gold. But I am got into an excellent ſubject, and I forget my ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151189:19"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, walk with God <hi>nimbly;</hi> quicken your pace, and go faſt in the way of God; ſtrive who ſhould go the faſteſt, to be as the Diſciple that out-ran <hi>Peter</hi> to the Sepulcher, <hi>John</hi> 20.4. <hi>I will run the way of thy Commandments;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John. 20.4. Pſal. 119.32.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> would not <hi>creep</hi> to Heaven, but he would <hi>run</hi> to Heaven. What a ſhame is it? many <hi>run</hi> to <hi>Hell,</hi> and we do but <hi>creep</hi> to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> ſome make <hi>haſte</hi> to get <hi>wealth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 28 22.</note> and we are <hi>ſlow</hi> in getting <hi>glory.</hi> Let me tell you this, the <hi>faſter</hi> you <hi>walk,</hi> the ſooner you'l come to your <hi>journeys</hi> end. But if we go ſo <hi>faſt,</hi> we <hi>fear</hi> we ſhall be <hi>weary</hi> and <hi>faint;</hi> You have an excellent Promiſe to prevent this objection.<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.30.31.</note> 
               <hi>Even the youths ſhall faint and be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the young men ſhall utterly fall; but they that wait upon the Lord ſhal renew their ſtrength, they ſhal mount up with wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, and they ſhall walk and not faint. Natural motion</hi> ſpends <hi>ſtrength,</hi> but <hi>ſpiritual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> increaſes <hi>ſtrength,</hi> here the way to <hi>do much,</hi> is to <hi>do much.</hi> But they that would go <hi>apace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magno viatico breve iter vitae non inſtruitur; ſed oneratur. <hi>Min Foelix.</hi> Heb. 12.1.</note> muſt not burden themſelvs with any <hi>weighty</hi> things: the world is a <hi>weight,</hi> ſin is a <hi>weight Let us therefore lay aſide every weight, and let us run with patience the race that is ſet before us.</hi> There muſt be <hi>patience,</hi> becauſe ſometimes the <hi>way</hi> is <hi>bad;</hi> and there muſt be <hi>running</hi> or nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, becauſe the way is long.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eighthly, walk with God <hi>cheerfully. Rejoyce in God alwayes; and again, I ſay, rejoyce:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.4.</note> The <hi>gemination</hi> of the <hi>command</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues the <hi>difficulty</hi> of the <hi>duty,</hi> and the <hi>excellency</hi> of the <hi>duty.</hi> God loves a <hi>cheerful giver,</hi> and he alſo loves a <hi>cheerful liver.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.7.</note> Nothing doth more <hi>honour</hi> Religion, then the cheerfulneſs of them that poſſeſs it.<note place="margin">Spiritus Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſticus eſt Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicus.</note> Is not this one of the reproaches that wicked men caſt upon the people of God? they are heavy, ſad, drooping, melancholly men, there's no mirth amongſt them; wipe off this reproach by a cheerful walking: I do not preſs upon you the <hi>fooliſh, frothy, carnal</hi> mirth of the world, but that which is <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>comely.</hi> Lift up your heads, give not way to dejectedneſs. <hi>The joy of the Lord is your ſtrength.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 8.10. Prov. 15.1.3.</note> 
               <hi>By ſorrow of heart the ſpirit is broken;</hi> it <hi>breaks</hi> the <hi>countenance,</hi> it <hi>enfeebles</hi> the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> who ſhould be cheerful if not you? <hi>Why art thou ſo ſad from day to day, ſeeing thou art the Kings Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.5.</note> ſaid <hi>Jonadab</hi> to <hi>Amnon?</hi> Is <hi>God</hi> your <hi>Father, Chriſt</hi> your <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151189:20"/>Heaven</hi> your <hi>inheritance,</hi> Everlaſting <hi>Joy</hi> your <hi>portion;</hi> notwithſtanding all this, will <hi>you</hi> be <hi>ſad?</hi> But we are thus and thus <hi>afflicted.</hi> Be it ſo: Yet rejoyce, your <hi>ſin</hi> is <hi>pardoned,</hi> this makes affliction to be no affliction. <hi>And the inhabitant ſhall not ſay, I am ſick; the people that dwell therein ſhall be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven their iniquity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ſa. 33.24.</note> But we are often under the ſad withdrawing of God. Be it ſo, yet rejoyce. <hi>For a ſmall moment have I forſaken thee, but with great mercies will I gather thee.</hi> But we are to <hi>mourn</hi> for ſin.<note place="margin">ſa. 54.7.</note> True, but one duty muſt not juſtle out another. Even in this <hi>ſorrow</hi> there is matter of <hi>joy,</hi> and this ſorrow is very well conſiſtent with ſpiritual rejoycing.<note place="margin">Verus poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s de peccatis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; de do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re gauder.</note> I might inſtance in other things; pray labour to be cheerful: 'tis not onely your <hi>priviledge,</hi> but your <hi>duty;</hi> which if you will diſcharge (not from the <hi>conſtitution</hi> or <hi>temper</hi> of the body, but) from <hi>Goſpel-Principles</hi> and <hi>motives,</hi> it will be highly pleaſing to God, and much to the <hi>creduit</hi> of your profeſſion; <hi>Daniel</hi> with his <hi>pulſe</hi> to look ſo well!<note place="margin">Dan. 1.15.</note> ſurely there's ſomething in it; when wicked men ſhall ſee you, though under afflictions, to bear up cheerful, ſurely they will ſay, There's <hi>ſomething excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninthly and laſtly, Walk with God <hi>conſtantly</hi> and <hi>perſvee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Indeſinenter ambulavit. <hi>Jun.</hi>
               </note> Thus <hi>Enoch</hi> walked (as hath been already hinted) 'tis not a turne or two that will do the buſineſſe; you muſt <hi>perſevere</hi> in the way of <hi>Holineſs.</hi> I beſeech you take heed of <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> a ſin never more common then in this Age; that indeed if the Scripture was not very clear, as to this point, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was there ſo much cauſe to <hi>queſtion</hi> the truth of that <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Saints Perſeverance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.12. Heb. 10.3. Mat. 10.22. Revel, 3.11. 2 Epiſt. of <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.</note> as now. But there's no diſputing from the <hi>meteor</hi> to the <hi>fixed</hi> Star. Hold on in your way, do not depart from the <hi>living God. If any man draw back, my ſoule ſhall take no pleaſure in him.</hi> 'Tis your perſeverance that muſt <hi>crown</hi> all. <hi>He that endureth to the end, he ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Recedente ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia recedat neceſſe eſ &amp; corona, <hi>Cypr. de Unit. Eccl.</hi> 2 Pet. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>Hold that faſt which thou haſt, that no man take thy Crown. Loſe not that which ye have wrought, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a full reward.</hi> Better ye had never <hi>entred</hi> upon this walk, then not to continue in it; Can ye be better then in Gods wayes? Are <hi>Egypts onions</hi> better then <hi>Canaans grapes?</hi> Will you leave the <hi>joyes</hi> of <hi>holineſs</hi> for the <hi>pleaſures of ſin?</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151189:20"/>Are you not within <hi>ſight</hi> of the place of <hi>reſt,</hi> and will you now <hi>turn back?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Turpe eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extremo defice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Luk. 14.34.</note> will you <hi>repent</hi> of your <hi>walking</hi> with God when you come to <hi>die?</hi> if you leave him, will you be any thing but <hi>ſalt that hath l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt its ſavour, that's good for nothing but to be thrown to the dunghill?</hi> The <hi>Lord,</hi> even <hi>God</hi> our <hi>Father,</hi> ſo <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh you,</hi> that you may ſo <hi>walk,</hi> and ſo <hi>run,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.24.</note> that ye may <hi>obtain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the <hi>Directive</hi> part. I now come to the <hi>Perſwaſive</hi> part, to exhort and preſs you to this bleſſed walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with God.</p>
            <p>To prevail with you herein, I might lay before you ſeveral Arguments, drawn from the <hi>preſent ſtate.</hi> As</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, 'tis the <hi>ſafeſt</hi> walking; He that walks with God, he's under the <hi>Protection</hi> of Heaven, nothing can hurt him; <hi>He ſhal dwell on High, his place of defence ſhall be the munitions of rocks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.16. Pſal. 90.1. Iob. 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall abide under the ſhadow of the Almighty. His Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle ſhal be in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, as there is <hi>ſafe protection,</hi> ſo there is <hi>abundant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion</hi> in this walking with God. Here's no <hi>danger</hi> to be <hi>feared,</hi> here's no <hi>good</hi> to be <hi>wanted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10.</note> 
               <hi>The young Lions do lack and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeek the Lord ſhall not want any good thing: Bread ſhall be given him, his waters ſhall be ſure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this is the <hi>ſweeteſt</hi> walking, What are all the joys of carnal men, to the joyes and comforts which are to be found in an holy life? <hi>Wiſdoms wayes are wayes of pleaſantneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3.16. Iſa. 64.5.</note> 
               <hi>and all her paths are peace. Thou meeteſt him that rejoyceth and worketh righteouſneſs, thoſe that remember thee in thy wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, this is the moſt <hi>honourable</hi> and <hi>glorious</hi> walking. It puts a glory upon the creature to walk with his <hi>Creatour;</hi> as 'tis an honour to the beggar to walk with a King. Holy men are glory it ſelfe. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon all the glory ſhall be a defence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Faith puts a Glory upon the Perſon, and Holineſs upon the Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, this walking <hi>pleaſes</hi> God. <hi>Enoch had this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that he pleaſed God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.5.</note> His walking with God was pleaſing God. I might very much enlarge upon theſe and ſuch other Arguments: but I paſs them by, and ſhall onely inſiſt upon the great <hi>Motive</hi> in the text: Walk with God on <hi>Earth,</hi> and <hi>live with God</hi> in <hi>Heaven. And he was not, for God took him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151189:21"/>
            <p>And ſo I paſſe from <hi>Enochs Holineſs,</hi> to <hi>Enochs Happineſs.</hi> Here I might enter upon a very large diſcourſe from this clauſe, but I'le onely open the ſenſe of the words, and then ſhew you what there is in them, to ſtir you up to walk with God.</p>
            <p>To all the reſt its ſaid, <hi>And he died, And he died,</hi> but here's a <hi>variation</hi> of the phraſe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>He was not, &amp;c.</hi> In the <hi>Hebrew</hi> 'tis, <hi>And not he, for God took him.</hi> Some make the words to hold out <hi>Enochs death. And not he,</hi> (that is, he died) <hi>God took him,</hi> (that is) away by a ſudden and untimely death: And ſo 'tis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.36. <hi>Joſeph is not, and Simeon is not,</hi> and <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.15. <hi>Rachel weeping for her Children, refuſed to be comforted, becauſe they were not,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> they were dead) and ſo for the other expreſſion, ſaith <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 Kings 19.4. <hi>It is enough now,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sumpſit eum Deus <hi>i. e.</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus eſt. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben-Ezra.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O Lord, take away my life.</hi> And thus the Jewiſh Doctors do expound the words. But this is directly contrary to what we have in the New Teſtament, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5. <hi>By faith Enoch was tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death. Ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſter</hi> ſayes from hence, 'tis probable he did not dye; and <hi>Druſius</hi> with his wit would enervate the ſtrength of the place,<note place="margin">Druſ. in Praef. ad Henoch Perer. de tranſ. Enoch quaeſt. <hi>1.</hi> Rivet Exercit. <hi>49.</hi> in Gen. <hi>Non erat, quia non mori eum fecit Deus.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Septuag.</note> by ſeveral evaſions which he ſuggeſts, but both are cenſured; <hi>Pererius</hi> blames the one, and <hi>Rivet</hi> the other.</p>
            <p>In the general, all the learned agree in this, that <hi>Enoch</hi> did not die, but that he was in an extraordinary manner tranſlated hence, ſo the <hi>Targum</hi> renders it; <hi>God made him not to dye:</hi> ſo the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> juſt as you have it. <hi>Heb,</hi> 11.5. <hi>He was not found, for God had tranſlated him.</hi> But if we come to particulars, we ſhall find a difference betwixt the Proteſtant and the Popiſh Writers, and that in two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. As to the <hi>Place,</hi> whither he was <hi>tranſlated.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. As to his <hi>unalterable permanſion</hi> or <hi>continuance</hi> in that <hi>place,</hi> whatever it is.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, he was tranſlated into <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> where <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were put in the ſtate of their innocency. There <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> and ſome others, are placed by God, there to continue in a very happy ſtate for ſome time. Many of the Papiſts themſelves do not greatly fancy this opinion; for ſome of them do agree with us,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.7.</note> as to <hi>Enochs Tranſlation</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151189:21"/>to the <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and others deny that that Paradiſe into which our firſt Parents were put, is yet in continuance. No 'twas loſt in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Deluge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Percr. diſp. de Enoch.</note> But others of them are very hot upon it, as <hi>Bellarmine, Leſſius; Sextus Senenſis, &amp;c.</hi> And ſome of the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> are of their ſide,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Dicere Henoch &amp; Eliam non eſſe tranſlatos in illum Para. diſum terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrem inibique verſari, eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra divinam Scripturam, &amp; à fidei regulâ exorbitare. <hi>Sixtus Sen. Bibl. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Annot.</hi> 36. <hi>Juſt Mart. Quaeſt. &amp; reſp. ad Orthod. in Reſp. ad Qu.</hi> 85.</p>
                  <p>Dicunt Presbyteri qui ſunt Apoſtolorum Diſcipuli, eos qui tranſlati ſunt, illuc tranſlatos eſſe <hi>Iren. Adv. Haereſ. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſpeaks expreſly the ſame; ſo doth <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and ſome others: and the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Theodor. Qu. in Gen. Inter. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> reſt of them generally ſpeak <hi>modeſtly,</hi> as being rather for a <hi>ſober ſilence</hi> then a too <hi>curious inquiry</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this ſecret, which the Scripture doth not clearly make out to us.<note n="*">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Et quae ſequuntur. <hi>Chryſoſt. Hom.</hi> 21 <hi>in Gen.</hi> Quid de Hellia factum ſit neſcimus; hoc de illo tamen credimus, quod vera Scriptura teſtatur. <hi>Aug. contra. Fauſtum Manich.</hi> Quò raptus fuerit Deus novit. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Divines</hi> on the other hand aſſert, that <hi>Enoch</hi> was <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated</hi> into <hi>Heaven,</hi> the <hi>Coelum Empyraum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gerh. l.</hi> 8. <hi>de Mor.</hi> 1.163, &amp;c. <hi>Rivet. Exercit.</hi> 49. <hi>in Gen.</hi> Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> upon <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5 <hi>Calvin ſeems to differ,</hi> Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tamen in coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtem, gloriam tranſlatus eſt; ſed tantùm prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentis vitae mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriis ſolutus, donec veniret Chriſtus reſurgentium primitiae. <hi>Rivet givee you his ſenſe in theſe words,</hi> in Exercit. piiùs citatâ.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peter Martyr alſo ſpeaks ambiguouſly.</hi> Loc. Com. Cl. 32 c. 16. de raptu Heliae &amp; Henoch.</p>
               </note> the <hi>place</hi> of the <hi>bleſſed,</hi> both <hi>ſoul</hi> and <hi>body,</hi> and that he is now there <hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> in a ſtate of <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> and <hi>perfection.</hi> 'Twas with <hi>Enoch</hi> in his <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> as it was with <hi>Elias</hi> in his; but of him 'tis ſaid, <hi>he went up by a Whirlwind into Heaven,</hi> 2 King 2.11. thither therefore did <hi>Enoch</hi> go alſo. Much is ſpoken for the juſtifying of this opinion though when all is done, the judgement will not be under ſo full a command to aſſent to it, becauſe the word is ſilent, or at leaſt doth not ſpeak ſo expreſly to it. They that will pleaſe to inquire further into it, may turn to the Authors cited in the Margent.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:151189:22"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A ſecond difference is as to <hi>Enochs Permanſion,</hi> in that <hi>ſtate</hi> into which he is <hi>tranſlated.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay he did not die, but he ſhall come again,<note place="margin">Nondum He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch eſt mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ſed morietur tamen aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, quia ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, &amp;c. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin in Com. ad ep. ad Hebr.</hi>
               </note> and then he ſhall be ſubject to death as others are; and at this comming he ſhal appear with <hi>Elias,</hi> as the <hi>two witneſſes</hi> that <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of, and ſo he ſhall be ſlain. We ſay, <hi>he never died</hi> (againſt the Jew) <hi>and never ſhal die</hi> (againſt the Papiſt) his Paſſe to glory was extraordinary, and ſo he falls in with thoſe whom the Lord ſhall find alive at his ſecond coming <hi>they ſhall all</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.51.</note> 
               <hi>be changed,</hi> but they ſhal not die. 'Tis true, 'tis appointed to <hi>all men once to die,</hi> but yet God can grant an <hi>exemption</hi> or <hi>extraordinary diſpenſation</hi> where he will,<note place="margin">Si quis illud Apoſtoli obji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat, conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um eſſe omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſemel mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, facilis eſt ſolutio, quòd mors non ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſit Divorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um animáe à corpore, led mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri dicuntur, qui corruptibilem exuunt naturam, qualis erit mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>um quos dies ultimus ſuperſtite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inveniet. <hi>Calv. ad loc.</hi> Rom. 5.14. Id intelligi debet de mortis jure in omnes; non quò<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deus nullos a morte poſſit eximere. <hi>Rivet.</hi> Moritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; qui de mutatur. <hi>Draſ.</hi>
               </note> for he is not ſo thereby bound, but he can act as he pleaſes. And whereas 'tis ſaid, <hi>All have ſinned, and therefore death hath paſſed upon all;</hi> that is to be underſtood in point of <hi>guilt,</hi> which makes all <hi>obnoxious</hi> to death, and to deſerve the inflicting of that as the puniſhment of ſin, yet God may give a <hi>relaxation</hi> out of his <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>gracious Soveraignty.</hi> The objections of our adverſaries are not conſiderable further, then in what hath been hinted, and therefore I will not ſtay upon them.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly given you the ſenſe of the words, I ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now draw out the ſtrength of them by way of motive to preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you upon this holy walking with God. There are three thing that have a great <hi>emph ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>God took him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>God took him immediately.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>He was fit for God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, I ſay, <hi>God took him</hi> (that is) to himſelf, to be where h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to enjoy his <hi>beatific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Preſence in Glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Joſeph. Ant. Jud. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. Hoc enim de Enoch legimus aut Eliah; fed &amp; tu rapieris in Spiritu. Ecce currus Eliae, ecce ignes, etſi non videntur, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tur, ut juſtus aſcendat, innocens transferatur, &amp; tua vita mori neſcit. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Enoch walked wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> God, and Enoch went to God.</hi> This is the happineſſe of ever child of God that walks with him, whenever he dies God take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him. <hi>Enochs paſſage</hi> was <hi>extraordinary: He was not,</hi> that wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151189:22"/>to himſelfe, but <hi>Enochs</hi> Glory; for the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of it, <hi>every</hi> holy man hath it; <hi>God took him,</hi> that's a happineſs in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all, of whom I am ſpeaking. Let a true Chriſtian go out of the world which way God pleaſes; with God he is, with God he reſts. <hi>Death</hi> doth but bring ſuch into their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Preſence,</hi> that's all the <hi>hurt</hi> it doth them. Here in the body they are abſent <hi>from the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.6. Phil. 1.23.</note> death brings them into the <hi>Preſence Chamber;</hi> when they are diſſolved, they are <hi>with Chriſt.</hi> Is it ſo? who then would not walk with God? To be with God, I ſay it again, to be with God, what tongue can expreſs, what heart can conceive what this is! 'Tis a bleſſed thing to be with the <hi>Angels</hi> (thoſe that <hi>ſtand by,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 3.7. Heb. 12.23 Matth. 8.11.</note> as the Prophet ſpeaks) with the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>firſt-born,</hi> the old <hi>Patriarchs, Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; what's <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> to <hi>Paul</hi> on the <hi>Throne,</hi> (and yet that was one thing which <hi>Auſtin</hi> would have deſired to ſee) but what's all this to be with God Himſelfe?<note place="margin">Revel. 7.17. 1 Cor. 13.9.10. Matth. 25.23, 1 Theſ. 4.17. Revel. 14.13. Pſal. 84.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Cor. 4.17, 1 Cor. 13.11. Matth. 7.23. 2 Theſ. 1.9. Pſal. 16. ult.</note> what's the <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>Star</hi> to the <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>Sun!</hi> To be with God, what is it? Never to <hi>ſin</hi> more, never to <hi>ſorrow</hi> more, to be made <hi>perfect,</hi> to <hi>inherit</hi> his <hi>own glory,</hi> to have <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted communion</hi> with him, to be at <hi>reſt,</hi> alwayes <hi>praiſing</hi> God, <hi>preſſed</hi> down with nothing but a <hi>weight</hi> of <hi>glory.</hi> I ſpeak much, and yet how like a child do I ſpeak, (and well may I ſpeak but ſo, when <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe thinks he ſpeaks but as a <hi>child,</hi> in the ſetting out of this infinite glory.) Well, walk with God, and all this yours: when others are ſent away with a <hi>Depart from me,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi> Enoch tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt in carne. Elias carneus raptus eſtin coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum; nec dum mortui &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſi jam colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, quod nos imitamur je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junio illi poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Deicon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortio, &amp;c. <hi>Hier. ad Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſeparated</hi> from the Preſence of the Lord, you ſhall be with him, and lie in his boſome, in whoſe <hi>Preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>God took him immediately.</hi> He was not put into ſome <hi>third</hi> place, a <hi>Limbus Patru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> an <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome (diſtinct from Heaven) there to be a <hi>Probationer</hi> or an <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> No! <hi>Enoch</hi> in his <hi>life</hi> was <hi>candidatus aternitatis,</hi> after his <hi>Change,</hi> he was not <hi>candidatus gloriae,</hi> but <hi>poſſeſſor glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae.</hi> Thus it is with every <hi>holy Walker, He is not, and God takes him,</hi> as ſoon as the <hi>breath</hi> is out of his <hi>body, immediately</hi> he is with God; 'tis ſhort a <hi>cut,</hi> from the <hi>ſick bed</hi> to the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151189:23"/>Throne.</hi> The body ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, like <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ahs m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a little behind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to be looked up here in a <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>binet</hi> of <hi>duſt,</hi> but the ſoule ſtayes not, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akes 3. <hi>quick</hi> and <hi>ſtraight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ight</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s God. The <hi>body</hi> ſleeps.<note place="margin">Gerh. de morte in fine.</note> but the ſoule knows no ſuch thing (they are aſleep themſelves that dream of ſuch a thing) it doth not go to the <hi>pillow,</hi> but to the<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 7.9. <hi>Pſychopann.</hi> Luk. 23.43.</note> 
               <hi>white rob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> 'tis <hi>Calvins</hi> expreſſion <hi>Verily, I ſay unto thee, to day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe</hi> The <hi>Thiefe</hi> made <hi>Chriſt</hi> to wait long for his <hi>repenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce,</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> will not make him to ſtay a jot for his <hi>glory:</hi> 'tis bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>crucified</hi> by <hi>man,</hi> and <hi>glorified by God.</hi> Will not this engage you to walk with God? who can hear theſe things, and not be wrought upon? I beſeech you thus walk, and you have but one <hi>journey</hi> more, and that is <hi>to go to God,</hi> and that ſhall be done in a <hi>moment;</hi> you go but ſlowly <hi>towards Heaven,</hi> you ſhall go apace into <hi>Heaven. Sin</hi> hinders you in your <hi>motion</hi> in <hi>grace,</hi> nothing ſhall hinder you in your <hi>motion to glory</hi> (i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſoul may be ſaid to move.)</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Enoch</hi> was <hi>fit</hi> for God, or meet for God. <hi>He walked with God, and was not, God took him.</hi> Here was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to be done for <hi>Enoch.</hi> but to take him. We ſay in Philoſophy, God and Nature do nothing <hi>per ſaltum;</hi> it holds true here; God doth not take a ſinner <hi>reeking</hi> in his <hi>luſt,</hi> and preſently make him an <hi>heir</hi> of glory; no, God <hi>prepares</hi> him for it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng thanks to the Father, who hath made us meet to be Partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi> The <hi>cloth</hi> will not receive the <hi>ſcarlet tincture</hi> at firſt, but it muſt be prepared by ſome <hi>lighter colours;</hi> thus 'tis here, firſt there muſt be the <hi>tincture</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> ſo to make way for the <hi>tincture of glory.</hi> If God ſhould take one that was not an <hi>Enoch</hi> to himſelfe, he would long to be from him again, <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> would be worſe then <hi>Hell</hi> to him. Here's another motive then to ſtir you up to walk with God; then you are fit for God. You muſt be <hi>prepared</hi> for Heaven, as well as Heaven i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>prepared</hi> for you.<note place="margin">John 14, 2.</note> Thus you cannot be, unleſs you walk with God, for <hi>holineſs</hi> is our <hi>idoneity,</hi> or <hi>aptitude,</hi> or <hi>meetneſs</hi> for glory.<note place="margin">Act. 1.15.</note> The <hi>unholy</hi> man is fit for <hi>hell, Judas went unto his own place.</hi> The <hi>holy</hi> man is fit for <hi>Heaven, Enoch went to his own place.</hi> Be thus, and then ſay, Lord, I am <hi>ready,</hi> my <hi>work</hi> is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151189:23"/>done, my <hi>heart</hi> is prepared, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>come</hi> and <hi>take</hi> me <hi>quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of all is this, Go home and be <hi>Enoch Walkers</hi> for the time to come; as you deſire to be with God in the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> walk with God in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Grace.</hi> Thus <hi>live,</hi> and thus <hi>die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the <hi>ſecond</hi> Uſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3.</note> I might add a <hi>third</hi> to <hi>help</hi> you in this walking with God. I have directed you as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and manner; but ſome may ſay, what ſhall we do that we may thus walk with God? 'Tis time to break off from this diſcourſe, otherwiſe I might inlarge upon theſe <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, if you would walk with God, <hi>you muſt get out of a ſtate of nature.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Inanimate</hi> things do not <hi>move, motion</hi> is onely proper to things that have <hi>life;</hi> men in their natural eſtate are dead, they cannot walk; ſpeak to them of this, 'tis in vain, <hi>aliquid deeſt,</hi> as he ſaid of the <hi>Statue,</hi> there wanted a <hi>ſoul,</hi> here an <hi>inward principle</hi> of life. <hi>Opportet eſſe aliquid eſſe intus,</hi> as to this walking with God. The <hi>Watch</hi> may go right for an hour or two, but 'twill not hold if the <hi>Springe</hi> be amiſſe. <hi>Natural</hi> men may take a <hi>pace</hi> or two in the waies of God, but they cannot <hi>walk</hi> unleſſe the Springe he right, unleſſe the <hi>heart</hi> be <hi>renewed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Serious conſideration is very requiſite to this walk. Ponder the path of thy feet. I thought on my waies, and turned my feet unto thy teſtimonies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 4.26. Pſal. 119.59.</note> The <hi>holy</hi> man is the <hi>conſidering</hi> man. He that is not <hi>much</hi> in the <hi>duty</hi> of <hi>meditation,</hi> will be <hi>little</hi> in the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>holineſſe.</hi> Every day conſider <hi>how</hi> you walk, <hi>where</hi> you walk, what your <hi>temptations</hi> are, what <hi>ſnares</hi> are laid for you, that you may avoid them, what your way is, that you may keep in it: this will much help you in your walking with God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>take in the ſtrength of God to enable you thus to walk;</hi> for you cannot walk <hi>with God without God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sine ipſo cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ipſo ambulare impoſſibile eſt. <hi>Halls Enoch.</hi> Jer. 19.23.</note> 
               <hi>The way of man is not in himſelf, it is not in man that walketh to direct his steps.</hi> If God do not <hi>guide</hi> you, you will <hi>loſe</hi> your way; if God do not <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> you, you will <hi>faint</hi> in the way; if God doth not by the <hi>influences</hi> of his <hi>grace,</hi> put you into the way, you will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151189:24"/>
               <hi>get</hi> into it. Oh, <hi>pray</hi> that you may thus <hi>walk,</hi> the more <hi>dependently</hi> you live <hi>on</hi> God, the cloſer you will walk <hi>with</hi> God, the <hi>leſſe</hi> there is of <hi>ſelf,</hi> the <hi>more</hi> there will be of <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Now the God of Peace, that brought again from the dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.20.21.</note> 
               <hi>that great Shepheard of the Sheep, through the blood of the everlaſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good work to do his Will, working in you that which is wel-pleaſing in his ſight,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> this holy walking) <hi>through Jeſus Chriſt, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whom be glory for ever and ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the <hi>Text,</hi> I now come to the <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> the preſent <hi>afflictive</hi> Providence, which is the occaſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this ſad and ſolemn Aſſembly: And that is the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Richard Vines,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſoul is with God,</hi> whoſe body is with us now to be interred; confident I am, here are many hundreds in this Congregation, that coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>drop</hi> many <hi>tears</hi> into that <hi>grave,</hi> where this <hi>once uſeful body</hi> is now to be laid up as an <hi>uſeleſſe piece of clay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not be long in this diſcourſe; and before I enter upon it, I muſt tell you that I am very ſenſible of my unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for this work, from firſt to laſt and therefore with muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> regret and fear (the Lord knows) did ingage in it. Alas I am but a <hi>man</hi> of <hi>yeſterday,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 8.9.</note> a Novice, for me to do this laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Office for ſuch a man as our deceaſed Father and Brother was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that too in the preſence of ſo many <hi>grave judicious, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters,</hi> who may be my fathers, truly I bluſh at it but you may all ſpare your cenſuring of me, for I do very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely cenſure my ſelf. All this had been prevented (t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your, I am ſure to my own great comfort and ſatisfaction) i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> another darkiſh Providence had not interpoſed. There was worthy perſon deſign'd firſt to this work, one whoſe head an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heart God hath inured to Funeral Sermons, one who was int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately acquainted with him that is dead and gone, and ſo ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been for many years, one who was as willing as fit for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſervice, but he is at preſent Gods Priſoner, and diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inable<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by diſtempers of body: The Lord continue his life, that he may preach many Sermons more, but no more Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for ſuch inſtruments as this our brother was if the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſe. But we'l leave the <hi>Apology,</hi> and come to the buſineſs
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151189:24"/>Another of the <hi>Chariots</hi> and <hi>Horſemen</hi> of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> is gone:<note place="margin">2 Kings 2.12. 2 Sam. 23.</note> one of the <hi>three,</hi> not one of the <hi>thirty,</hi> for he may well be put amongſt the firſt, as exceeding the moſt, inferiour to none. We may this day ſay to God, with an <hi>humble ſubmiſſion</hi> to him under his correcting diſpenſations, as to the death of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>Joſeph is not, and Simeon is not, and ye wil take away Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, all this is againſt me.</hi> Dr. <hi>Gouge</hi> is not, Mr. <hi>Gataker</hi> is not, Mr. <hi>Strong</hi> is not, Mr. <hi>Robinſon</hi> is not,<note place="margin">Gen. 42.36.</note> my dear and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous friends, Dr. <hi>Hill</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> are not, of late worthy memory M. <hi>Marſhal</hi> is not; all theſe <hi>are not,</hi> and now <hi>Benjamin</hi> is gone too. Theſe things are very ſad, the Lord help us to lay them to heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hiſtorical Narratives</hi> are very uſual upon this occaſion, I ſhall be very ſhort in mine.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> was born at <hi>Blazon</hi> in the County of <hi>Lieceſter:</hi> when he was of competent age, he was ſent to the Univerſity, where he continued for ſome years a Student in <hi>Magdalene Colledge.</hi> In which time he diſcovered much quickneſs of wit, and pregnancy of parts, which though they made him <hi>lively</hi> and <hi>acute,</hi> yet never <hi>ſinful</hi> or <hi>prophane</hi> (which is a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, when we conſider how apt your <hi>hot</hi> wits are to <hi>boil</hi> up to a <hi>ſcum</hi> of <hi>frothineſſe</hi> and <hi>prophaneneſſe.</hi>)</p>
            <p>From the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> he was removed to <hi>Hinckley</hi> in his own Country, where for ſome time he was a Schoolmaſter. And let this be no diſparagement; I could inſtance in rare inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Gods glory in the Church of Chriſt, who began with that emploiment; but Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> is enough to himſelf, and may rather give then take credit from any.</p>
            <p>From thence he was called to the Miniſtry at <hi>Weddington</hi> in the County of <hi>Warwick,</hi> where how diligent and painful he was in his work, 'tis ſufficiently known. Not bounding his parts and pains there, in the limits of a private village, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook a Lecture every fortnight at <hi>Non-eaton,</hi> which hee carried on with much profit too, and much applauſe from his hearers; inſomuch, that in thoſe days when preaching was a rare commodity, many both Miniſters and Chriſtians would travel many miles to hear him.</p>
            <p>The late and never enough to be lamented <hi>Civil war</hi> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151189:25"/>on, he was forced from his Houſe and Charge, for his Preſervation to go to <hi>Coventry:</hi> There he is not idle, and the inhabitants were ſo affected to his Miniſtry, that they ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired him to ſit down with them. And indeed 'tis <hi>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that great lights ſhould burn out in little rooms.</hi> The <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> calling an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines,</hi> he was nominated a Member of it, and deputed to have a ſhare in that work: And 'twas a mercy to the Church of God that he was ſo, for how much ſervice he did there in the matter of <hi>Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> may ſafely be concealed, ſcarcely be expreſt without offence.</p>
            <p>This was the occaſion of his coming up to this famous <hi>City:</hi> and here too, no ſooner was he come, but he had a call to <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Danes,</hi> a very large and conſiderable Pariſh. And how effectual his preaching there was to the good of many. Some I am ſure, in this Congregation can teſtifie, not without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tears, ſo much are they troubled at the drying up of thoſe breaſts, from which for ſome years they had ſo wholeſome nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>Afterwards he removed from thence to <hi>Watton</hi> in <hi>Hartford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> was alſo choſen to be Head of a Colledge in <hi>Cambridg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> viz. Pembroke-Hall,</hi> who more fit for learning, for a ſpirit of Government, for ſuch a truſt then he? there he continued very uſefull and ſerviceable, till he was put out, becauſe hee would not take the <hi>Engagement,</hi> I ſay, <hi>that Engagement</hi> which was a ſtone of ſtumbling, and a rock of offence, to many tender conſcientious Miniſters in this Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Raro ſolent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia inſigniter foelicia robuſta ſortiri corpora, ſic diſpenſante. Natura ut quod animi viribus additum eſt, corporis detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatur, <hi>Eraſm. in Ep. Praef. ad Aug. opera.</hi>
               </note> From being Paſtor of <hi>Waetton</hi> he was invited hither to <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Jury,</hi> and ſo returned to <hi>London</hi> again: <hi>And here this famous light went out.</hi> Hence was his laſt removal, <hi>viz. to glory.</hi> What his carriage and behaviour was here, you know better then I; and yet ſo much I know, that I dare confidently ſay, do but lay aſide ignorance and prejudice, and you cannot but bleſſe God that ever be came amongſt you:</p>
            <p>Long he had not been Miniſter here, but he fell into ſome <hi>decays</hi> and <hi>abatements,</hi> both in his ſpirit and ſtrength, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual pains in his head did ſomewhat cloud him, but yet <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> might be ſeen in the very <hi>duſt</hi> of it. Hee was formerly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151189:25"/>of a very ſtrong conſtitution, but lately infirmities grew much upon him, which he grapled withal ſome moneths to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, till God ſent his meſſenger with a <hi>final Arreſt</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake him away from us. At the Arrival of which upon <hi>Monday</hi> morning, betwixt two and three of the Clock he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied, at the Age of 56. or thereabouts. <hi>We bleſſe God he lived <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> long, we mourn becauſe he died ſo ſoon.</hi> And 'tis thought he hight have longer liv'd, had he wrought leſſe;<note place="margin">Job 14.14.</note> but why do ye ſpeak of that? <hi>His appointed time was come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we may bring my <hi>Text</hi> and the <hi>Providence</hi> together; or of our brother we may ſay, <hi>He walked with God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ut eſt mode ſtiae non agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere laudes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, it a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinis eſt non tacere vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, per quos numinis benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas tanta commoda lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur humano generi. <hi>Eraſ ib.</hi> John 5.35. Job 33 23. Acts 8.24. Ut v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa Aegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiis erepta in uſum Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naculi converti potuerunt, ſic Literatum &amp; Philoſophiae, ſtudia, &amp;c. <hi>Voet in orat Fun pro Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauo. p.</hi> 16.</note> and <hi>he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot,</hi> for <hi>God hath taken him.</hi> Shall we leave him thus! A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle I beſeech you of his <hi>worth:</hi> you have heard much from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, be willing to hear a little of him, partly to work upon our thankfulneſſe that you ever had him; partly, to work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon your ſorrow, that now you have loſt him; but chiefly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat God may have glory in raiſing up ſuch an inſtrument, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o rarely qualified and accompliſhed for his ſervice, I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o it very plainly; <hi>The Pearle needs no Art, tis beautiful e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ought in its own luſtre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was a burning and a ſhining light; An <hi>Interpreter,</hi> one of thouſand; of very great and eminent parts, taller by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead and ſhoulders then his ordinary brethren; A man <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighty</hi> in the Scriptures, another <hi>Apollos</hi> in that, exquiſitely accompliſhed in all parts of Learning; a perfect Maſter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Greek tongue; a good Philologer, an excellent Oratour, fitneſſe his curious and ingenious Oration, at the Funeral of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Noble <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> (in whoſe affections he had a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tereſt,) He was a ready and piercing Diſputant, and ſo he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pproved himſelf to admiration, in thoſe two famous Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, the one at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> the other at <hi>Newport</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight.</hi> He was a ſolid and moſt judicious Divine, who read ſuch, and concocted what he read, one who was able to give a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eighty and pithy deciſion in any controverted point. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as a notable Confuter of errours; <hi>He ſeldome ſpoke to them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut he hit the bird in the very eye, and made them die, not a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngring, but a ſudden death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.2.</note> In the courſe of his Miniſtery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was highly Orthodox, ſound in the faith, very powerful,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151189:26"/>very ſpirituall, his whole deſign and drift in his preaching, was to clear up that great doctrine of <hi>Juſtification</hi> (in which he was eminently ſtudied) to debaſe the <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of <hi>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In cordemco iſte unusregnat Articulus, in quem fluunt &amp; refluunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologicae cogi rationes d ù noctuque. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Iſa 50.4.</note> and to exalt the <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> He was one that knew how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to wounded ſpirits. There was a great<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Angell of Grantham.</hi> 2 Cor. 11.23. Vultis ut Do minusmeos ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venier s me of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendatotioſum? Calvini di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum <hi>Vid. Bcz. in vitâ Calv.</hi> Paſce ve. bo, paſce exemplo, paſce ſubſidio. Paſce verbo praedicationis doctè place ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplo conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fationis ſanctè paſce ſubſidio charitatis piè. <hi>Greg in Paſtor,</hi>
               </note> Light; who is now with God, who being under a ſore deſertion, did receive much comfort from him. His <hi>diligence</hi> in his work was great, in <hi>labours</hi> much, in <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> much; and to the laſt his great weakneſſes could not keep him from his Maſters work: that which would have made ſome kept their beds, could not keep him out of the Pulpit. <hi>The day before he died, being the Lords day, here he preached once, and adminiſtred the Lords Supper, and the day he died on, he was to preach a Funeral Sermon at Clements Danes.</hi> As he <hi>preach'd,</hi> ſo he <hi>liv'd;</hi> by his parts, he did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by his graces he did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, what he <hi>preach'd</hi> to others, he <hi>practiſ'd</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and was not like a <hi>way-mark,</hi> that ſhews others the way, but never ſtirs it ſelf.</p>
            <p>For his <hi>natural temper,</hi> he was a man of a brave undaunted ſpirit. Some called him <hi>Luther:</hi> indeed he was another <hi>Luther,</hi> he feared not the faces of any in the diſcharging of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. In his carriage he was ſomewhat blunt and inobſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, but not in the leaſt proud or ſupercilious. He was ſo <hi>unblameable</hi> and inoffenſive, that nothing can <hi>juſtly</hi> be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon him. Two things I know are in the mouths of many, His often removing from place to place; His covetouſneſs. For the former, there is no queſtion, but that in ſome caſes a Miniſter may<note n="*" place="margin">Vid Bowles. Paſt. Evangel. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> remove, (though herein for the avoiding of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, it concernes us to be very wary). And as to his particular caſe, I underſtand what his grounds were in all his removals, excepting only one, and am fully ſatisfied, that his removings upon them were lawful and warrantable, and ſo I ſuppoſe would his cenſurers be too, if they did but rightly underſtand how things were with him. For his covetouſneſſe, I ſuppoſe, by this time, that reproach is waſhed off; by what he hath left behinde him, it abundantly appears, <hi>His heart was not much in the world, if it had, ſure there would have been more of the world in his purſe.</hi> 'Tis not convenient to ſpeak out particulars, but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151189:26"/>this I may confidently ſay, <hi>There path not been a Miniſter of any repute in this City, for ſome yeares, who died with ſo mean an eſtate as he;</hi> and indeed, if the truth was known, they that cenſure him for this, would rather cenſure him upon another account.</p>
            <p>But to ſhut up all. Take him as a Chriſtian, he was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Enoch,</hi> a true Walker with God, a very holy man; more I can ſpeak of none, leſſe I cannot ſpeak of him. Thus he was, but now he is not, he is gone, we ſhall never hear him, nor ſee his face more. Oh! that's a cutting word.<note place="margin">Acts 20.38.</note> His life was like <hi>Enoch</hi>'s life, and his death very like to <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Tranſlation. He died ſuddenly. He went well to bed, ſlept and died. <hi>His death was a ſleep indeed;</hi> being weary and ſpent with his work, God took him to Heaven, there to give him a Cordial; from the Pulpit he went to the Throne; as ſoon as he had ended his Sabbath here, he entred upon his everlaſting Sabbath in glory. He went warme from his work to his wages, <hi>That's a bleſſed thing, for a Miniſter to be found by death about his Lords buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> His work was done, he had finiſhed his task, was wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and feeble. God his good Maſter takes him to himſelf, crownes him with life and immortality, and in ſtead of hard la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour here, calls him to that joyful work of ſinging forth prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> to his God and Father. And here we leave him. God grant that hither we may follow him.</p>
            <p>May be ſome will go home and ſay, I have ſpoke too much. My conſcience beares me witneſſe, I have ſpoke my heart, and what is the truth. He was a perſon of ſo much worth, that he doth go beyond all that I have ſpoken; for I may ſay of him with the Comedian, <hi>De quo non poſſum it â magnificè loqui,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Terent.</note> 
               <hi>Id virtus quin ſuperet ſua.</hi> But others will ſay, I have ſpoke too little; that I confeſſe is a truth, but that is my weakneſſe, not my fault. I muſt anſwer this too with that of the Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Lucan.</note>
               <l>Quòd ſi digna tuâ minus. eſt mea pagina laude,</l>
               <l>At voluiſſe ſat eſt.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>I ſhall crave leave to adde foure words to you, my ſad and ſerious Auditours, and ſo I ſhall diſmiſſe you. I ſhall ſpeak to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151189:27"/>you in a <hi>fourefold capacity;</hi> As <hi>private Chriſtians,</hi> As <hi>Miniſters,</hi> As <hi>Pariſhioners,</hi> As <hi>Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, as you are <hi>private Chriſtians;</hi> and in that conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let me hint a few things to you.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Be deeply affected with ſuch black Providences as this is.</hi> The <hi>loſſe</hi> of a Miniſter is a great <hi>loſſe.</hi> The death of a <hi>private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> is ſad, the death of a <hi>good Miniſter</hi> is more ſad, but the death of a <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>able</hi> Miniſter, ſuch a one as our brother was,<note place="margin">2 Kings 2.12.</note> this is very ſad indeed. <hi>My Father, my Father, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots of Iſrael, and the Horſemen thereof.</hi> The more publick is the loſſe, the more it is to be lamented: Godly Miniſters are men that are placed in a <hi>publick Orbe,</hi> and therefore their loſſe is much to be laid to heart. What do you loſe when you loſe your godly Miniſters? conſider what the Scripture makes them to be,<note place="margin">Ezck. 3.17. 1 Cor 4 1. 1 Cor. 4.15. Mat. 5 14.</note> 
               <hi>Watchmen, Stewards, Fathers, Lights, &amp;c.</hi> and you'll ſee you loſe much when they are taken away; and more then this, there cannot be a <hi>ſadder preſage</hi> of <hi>approaching judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to a Nation, then the <hi>death</hi> of ſuch. When God pulls up the ſtakes, he intends to burn the hedge; when the pillars are removed, the houſe is like to fall; upon theſe and other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, be ſeriouſly and deeply affected with ſuch diſpenſations as this is; God looks for this from you, and his Providences call you to it:<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.1.</note> but wo unto us, <hi>The righteous periſh, and no man layes it to heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Put away thoſe things which cauſe God to ſhorten the lives of painful Miniſters.</hi> I might reckon up many; you caſt dirt upon them, and God caſts duſt upon them; you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn them, and vilifie them; 'tis one of the ſins of the age. <hi>Jeroboam</hi> made Prieſts of the baſeſt of men; and now thoſe that ſerve in their ſtead, are made the baſeſt of men. The Heathens will riſe up in judgement againſt us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amongſt the Egypt: Prieſts were</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Diod. Sicul. Of Alexander. See Joſ. Ant, Jud l. <hi>11</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>who alwayes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured thoſe that adminiſtred in the matters of their worſhip.</hi> But I'le only inſtance in one thing: you are unfruitful and barren under all the paines of godly Miniſters: they preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, waſte their ſtrength, ſpend their lungs, preach out their very hearts, and yet you never the better: this makes God to take them away in judgement to you for your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſſe. 'Tis your ſin that haſtens their end; if you did thrive better, they would live longer.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151189:27"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>when you mourn becauſe ſo many are gone, be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful becauſe ſo many are left.</hi> God hath taken many <hi>Labourers</hi> out of his <hi>Vineyard</hi> in a little time; but many are yet ſpared: 'Tis of the Lords mercy, <hi>Eliſha</hi> is not ſnatch't away too. Well,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.25.</note> they are ſpared a little for the <hi>furtherance of your joy and faith: prize</hi> them, and <hi>profit</hi> by them, or elſe they alſo ſhall be removed from you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, let me take the boldneſſe to ſpeak a word to you my <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> in the <hi>Miniſtery.</hi> Though I am but an <hi>Elihu,</hi> yet ſuffer the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Exhortation</hi> from me.<note place="margin">Job. 32.6.</note> You ſee you are mortal as well as others, nay, indeed your lives are more uncertain then others: your frequent labours, your conſuming ſtudies, your ſpending emploiments drive you to the grave faſter then others. <hi>The Prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 1.5. 1 Cor. 15. ult.</note> 
               <hi>do they live for ever?</hi> I would from hence ſtir you up <hi>to abound in the work of the Lord,</hi> to improve your opportunities of ſervice whil'ſt health and ſtrength are afforded to you, to double your dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, to work <hi>whil'ſt the day laſts, becauſe the night is coming, when no man can work.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 9.4.</note> You are ſpared when others are taken away, there are <hi>fewer hands,</hi> you muſt be the more diligent; this may be will <hi>haſten</hi> death, but this I am ſure, it will <hi>ſweeten</hi> death, and make you go out of the world, if not with <hi>love</hi> from men, yet with <hi>peace</hi> in your own conſciences, 'twill be in the ſtead of a <hi>thouſand cordials</hi> to you when you come to die. <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt I have not been idle.</hi> I have according to my poor <hi>talent glorified thee on earth, and now glorifie thou me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 17.4.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be not too much caſt down at the taking away of ſuch <hi>eminent inſtruments</hi> as this was, for God will raiſe up others; he never wanted inſtruments as yet to do his work. If he take away an <hi>Eli,</hi> he'll provide a <hi>Samuel;</hi> if there be need of eminent inſtruments for the beating down of <hi>errour,</hi> the holding up of <hi>Truth.</hi> Such God will provide. He'll have an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> for an <hi>Arius,</hi> an <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for a <hi>Pelagius,</hi> a <hi>Proſper</hi> for a <hi>Coeleſtine,</hi> a <hi>Fulgentius</hi> for a <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> I ſay, let's not be caſt down, God will never want Workmen to do his work: only let us make this uſe of it, we that are <hi>remaining E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha</hi>'s, to get <hi>Elijah</hi>'s ſpirit doubled upon us, to treaſure up a large ſtock of grace and knowledge, that we may be able to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151189:28"/>bear ſome conſiderable weight when old pillars are gone; and to increaſe our diligence, as God increaſes our work.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, I ſhall ſuggeſt ſomething to you the Inhabitants of this Pariſh, who have the deepeſt ſhare in this ſad Providence, for though the <hi>Eclipſe</hi> reaches further; yet 'tis darkeſt in your borders. God hath ſmote your Shepherd, and you are like to be for a time as a ſcattered flock;<note place="margin">Zech. 13.7.</note> a Shepherd you may have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but every Shepherd is not Mr. <hi>Vines:</hi> ſhall I inminde you of two or three duties.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Bleſſe God for that merciful proviſion which he hath made for you, in a ſucceſſion of godly Paſtours. Not many places in this City have been better fed then you, to the praiſe of his Grace be it ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Study what is the meaning of God, in the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of your Miniſters ſo faſt. Two you have loſt in a little time, though by different wayes. The one burnt out like a candle, that hath no more matter to maintain its burning, the other was blowen out. This our brother, now to be interr'd was taken away by the Hand of God, the former Miniſter was taken away by the hand of man, whether juſtly or not, the great day will diſcover, when Kings and Parliaments muſt give a ſtrict account, eſpecially for blood, and that too eſpecially for the blood of precious Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Do not forget them, though you cannot enjoy them; Let the precious truths they preach'd, always be ſounding in your ears,<note place="margin">Heh. 11 4. Heb. 13.7.</note> for <hi>though they be dead, they do yet ſpeak. Remember them who have ſpoken to you the Word of God,</hi> though now they are laid aſide. You do remember them in ſome ſenſe, witneſſe the large expreſſions of your love to the widows, which the two laſt left behinde them, which I cannot but mention to your praiſe, but remember them further, ſo as to live according to that they have ſet before you. This affection is the beſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, this will be their crown and yours too at the day of judgement.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if I ſhall not preſume too far, let me adviſe you to be <hi>careful in your choice again;</hi> that when you ſhall come to that ſerious buſineſſe, you may pitch upon one, who by his Doctrine and Life, may build upon the ſame foundation, upon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151189:28"/>which your worthy Paſtours hitherto have done. My advice may be will give offence, but I hope my prayer will not; I heartily pray, that God will direct you herein to do that which may be moſt for his glory and your ſoules good.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſhall ſpeak to you the near and dear relations of this our deceaſed brother: you mourn, you have cauſe to mourn,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> we mourn with you, we lament for the publike, we ſympathize with you for your private affliction. You have loſt much, a dear husband, a loving father; but <hi>mourn not as without hope,</hi> quietly ſubmit to God, who hath put this cup into your hand.<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.13. 1 Sam. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>It is the Lord,</hi> be ſilent. He is gone, but whither? <hi>to be with God. He is not, but he is;</hi> He is not with you, but he is with Chriſt. He is taken, but God hath taken him; He that gave, he took; ſay; (though it be hard) <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord. If you lov'd me, you would rejoyce, becauſe I go unto my Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 1. ult. John 14.28.</note> He is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter where he is, then where he was; for here a poor decaying man, but there a glorious triumphing Saint. <hi>The Lord make up this great loſſe to you, to the Pariſh, to the City, to the whole Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="anagram">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151189:29"/>
            <head>RICHARD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S VINES.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Anagramma.</hi> Charus Dei Sinn.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>UNa deeſt Anagrammate litera, ſed tibi nullus</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>(O dilecte Deo) deſideratur apex.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>It's true, our Anagram doth limp a little</l>
            <l>That ſpeaks thy bliſſe; but it wants not a tittle.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Spurſtowe. D.D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>In memory of that eminent Servant of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>RICHARD VINES</hi> deceaſed, lately the learned and faithful Paſtour of <hi>Lawrence</hi> Church in <hi>London.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 13.23.</note>
            </head>
            <l>
               <hi>A</hi> Ponderous Cluſter once did give a taſte</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Paleſtines</hi> fertility and pleaſure</l>
            <l>To Zions Denizons, who in the Waſte</l>
            <l>Valu'd that Preſent as a royal treaſure;</l>
            <l>How fruitful was the <hi>Vine</hi> which bare that Cluſtre?</l>
            <l>How fertile was the ſoile which bred that <hi>Vine?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>How fragrant all its <hi>Vines</hi> then in their luſtre?<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.6.</note>
            </l>
            <l>How ſweet a Paradiſe was that holy <hi>Line?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Their <hi>Lines,</hi> I grant, were faire, our <hi>Lot</hi> is better,</l>
            <l>Theirs but a type was of our Promiſ'd Land;</l>
            <l>Their rich enjoyments were the bark and <hi>letter</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of what we look for in the Heavenly Strand.<note place="margin">Micah 7.1.</note>
            </l>
            <l>But wo is me when <hi>Vines</hi> begin to fail,</l>
            <l>Whence can we Grapes expect, or Cordials?</l>
            <l>In howling Deſert Zions Pilgrims quail</l>
            <l>At the report of <hi>Babels</hi> towering walls.</l>
            <l>How many <hi>Vines</hi> of late have been tranſplanted</l>
            <l>From wilderneſſe to Paradiſe? whoſe graces,</l>
            <l>Whoſe gifts and pains we in our journey wanted,</l>
            <l>Men of Seraphick principles and paces.</l>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:151189:29"/>
            <l>Their choice Perfections did in Thee unite,</l>
            <l>As in a common Centre all the Lines,</l>
            <l>Both Nature, Art and Grace thy name make bright,</l>
            <l>Each of them was a <hi>Vine,</hi> but thou art <hi>Vines.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Roger Drake,</hi> Paſtour of <hi>Peters Cheap.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>RICHARDUS VINES. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Hic rarus</hi> Videns<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam 9.9. Agite, eamus ad <hi>Videntem,</hi> nam qui Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta hodie, antiquitùs vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabatur <hi>Videns.</hi>
               </note>.</head>
            <l>HIc eſt ille <hi>Videns,</hi> quo non eſt rarior alter.</l>
            <l>Aſſertor Fidei; quo non nervoſior alter.</l>
            <l>Malleus Haereſium; quo non ſolertior alter.</l>
            <l>Praeco Dei verbi; quo non divinior alter.</l>
            <l>Nec vitae abſimilis voci; non ſanctior alter.</l>
            <l>Huic plures, Deus alme, pares concede <hi>Videntes.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>Ad Tumulum Viri quàm Clariſſimi, RICHARDI VINES, Aulae <hi>Pembrochianae</hi> nuper Praefecti. Malos <hi>Iambus</hi> enecat, beat bonos.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VIator! haud novum fero; fero malum:</l>
               <l>Diu eſt, quod omne Triſte non <hi>novum</hi> ſiet.</l>
               <l>Jacet, ſepulta Veritas; Sciens perit;</l>
               <l>Diémque vidit ultimum Pius ſuum.</l>
               <l>At Ilias mali ſequuta tot mala:</l>
               <l>In uno habemus omne. <hi>Vinius</hi> cadit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Malo</hi> vel auſus eſſe ſaeculo <hi>Bonus:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Minúſque dives eſſe, quàm pius minus.</l>
               <l>Frequenter <hi>Angliam</hi> dolere perfidam.</l>
               <l>Solumque Patrium ſolebat (O potens</l>
               <l>Fide!) imminente ſiſtere à ruina. At heu!</l>
               <l>Ruit Columna ponderi impar impari.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:151189:30"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ad haec: Sacrata Jura Numinis petens,</l>
               <l>Amoris ille plenus in Deum, niſi</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sacrum,</hi> nihil dein ſapit, nec appetit.</l>
               <l>Quam in infimis morari, obire maluit;</l>
               <l>Suprema quaeritans. <hi>Abit.</hi> (beata Mors!)</l>
               <l>Modis oportet hiſce Epiſcopum mori.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>P.V. Th.B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On his receiving the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> the day, (or rather ſome houres) before his death.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>STrange miracle! Elijah's</hi> bleſt repaſt.</l>
            <l>In fourty dayes brought him to God at laſt.</l>
            <l>But ſtranger this Our <hi>Vines</hi> to God does go</l>
            <l>In ſome few houres, and without fasting too.</l>
            <l>And yet in me, it ſhall no wonder move,</l>
            <l>A Raven did bring that: but this, a <hi>Dove.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Delicious fare! He reliſh'd nought beſide:</l>
            <l>But taſting of it, lik'd it not; and di'd.</l>
            <l>Yet ſtay, I'me out: for know, he is not dead,</l>
            <l>But after ſuch a <hi>Supper</hi> went to bed.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Pet. Vink. M.C. Lond.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Upon the Death of ſo many Reverend <hi>MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISTERS</hi> of late.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>STill we do finde black Cloth wears out the firſt;</l>
               <l>And fruits that are the choiceſt, keep the worſt.</l>
               <l>Such men? ſo many? and they die ſo faſt?</l>
               <l>They're precious (Death) Oh do not make ſuch waſte.</l>
               <l>Scarce have we dri'd our eyes for loſſe of one,</l>
               <l>But in comes tidings that another's gone.</l>
               <l>Oh that I had my former tears agen,</l>
               <l>(All but thoſe few laid out upon my ſin)</l>
               <l>Had I an Helicon in either eye,</l>
               <l>I have occaſion now to verſe them dry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Triumph (Licentious Age) lift up thy Song,</l>
               <l>Presbytery ſha'n't trouble you e're long;</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:151189:30"/>
               <l>Thoſe that tormented you before your day,</l>
               <l>Are now apace removing out o'th' way.</l>
               <l>Yea rather, tremble <hi>(England)</hi> ſtand agaſt,</l>
               <l>To ſee thy glorious Lamps go out ſo faſt;</l>
               <l>When Death (like <hi>Sampſon</hi>) thus layes hold upon</l>
               <l>The Pillars of the Church,—the Building's gone.</l>
               <l>When we do ſee ſo many ſtars to fall,</l>
               <l>Surely, it boads the worlds great Funeral.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>London,</hi> look to't, and think what Heaven is doing.</l>
               <l>Thy flames are coming, when thy Lots are going.</l>
               <l>Well may we all feare God intendeth wars,</l>
               <l>When he commands home his Ambaſſadours.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That venerable Synod, which of late</l>
               <l>Was made the object of mens ſcorne and hate,</l>
               <l>(For want of Copes and Miters, not of Graces,)</l>
               <l>Are now call'd up (with <hi>Moſes</hi>) and their faces</l>
               <l>When they return, ſhall ſhine; God ſees it fit,</l>
               <l>Such an Aſſembly ſhould in glory ſit.</l>
               <l>The learned <hi>Twiſſe</hi> went firſt, (it was his right)</l>
               <l>Then holy <hi>Palmer, Borroughs, Love, Gouge, White,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hill, Whitaker,</hi> grave <hi>Gataker,</hi> and <hi>Strong,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perne, Marſhal, Robinſon,</hi> all gone along.</l>
               <l>I have not nam'd them half: Their only ſtrife</l>
               <l>Hath been (of late) who ſhould firſt part with life.</l>
               <l>Thoſe few who yet ſurvive, ſick of this Age</l>
               <l>Long to have done their parts, and leave the Stage.</l>
               <l>Our Engliſh <hi>Luther, Vines,</hi> (whoſe death I weep)</l>
               <l>Stole away (and ſaid nothing) in a ſleep:</l>
               <l>Sweet (like a Swan) he preach't that day he went,</l>
               <l>And for his Cordial took a Sacrament:</l>
               <l>Had it but been ſuſpected,— he would die</l>
               <l>His people ſure had ſtopt him with their Cry.</l>
               <l>My blear-ey'd Muſe ('tis tears have made her ſo,)</l>
               <l>Muſt waſh his Marble too, before ſhe go.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>Upon the much to be lamented Death of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Vines.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>ARt thou gone too (thou great and gallant minde)</l>
            <l>And muſt ſuch Sneaks as I be left behinde?</l>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:151189:31"/>
            <l>If thus our Horſemen and Commanders die,</l>
            <l>What can the Infantry do then but flie?</l>
            <l>Oh divine <hi>Vines!</hi> Tell us, why would'ſt thou go,</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſſe thou could'ſt have left thy parts below?</l>
            <l>If there's a <hi>Metempſeuchoſis</hi> indeed,</l>
            <l>Tell us where we may finde thee at our need?</l>
            <l>Who hath thy Memory? thy Brain? thy Heart?</l>
            <l>Whom didſt thou leave thy tongue? (for every part</l>
            <l>Of thee can make a man) What if we finde,</l>
            <l>(As I'le not ſwear this Age wo'nt change her minde)</l>
            <l>Prelacy (though her lands are ſold) revive?</l>
            <l>Or Independency (who hopes to thrive</l>
            <l>No where ſuit's Trump) ſhould dare diſpute at length?</l>
            <l>Where haſt thou left thy Presbyterian ſtrength,</l>
            <l>With which thou got'ſt the Game, i'th' Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Where the King cri'd, that — <hi>Vines</hi> was in the right?</l>
            <l>When <hi>Eſſex</hi> di'd (the Honour of our Nation)</l>
            <l>Thou gav'ſt him a new life in thy Oration.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">An expreſſion in Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> Sermon on my Lord of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
               </note> But when great <hi>Fairfax</hi> to his Fate ſhall yield,</l>
            <l>Whom haſt thou left — to fetch from <hi>Naisby</hi> field</l>
            <l>Th' Immortal Turfe, and dreſſe it with a ſtory,</l>
            <l>That ſhall perpetuate his name and glory?</l>
            <l>Where's thy rich Fancy (man)? To whom (beneath)</l>
            <l>Did'ſt thou thy lofty and high ſtrain bequeath?</l>
            <l>Tell us for thy own ſake; for none but he</l>
            <l>That hath thy wit, can write thy Elegy.</l>
            <l>Till he be found, let this ſuffice, which I</l>
            <l>Leave on thy ſtone. — Here lies the Miniſtry.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. Wylde, Miniſter of Aynhoe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>In obitum Viri Doctiſſimi, pariter &amp; pientiſſimi, <hi>RICHARDI VINES,</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Summi Theologi.</head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <lg>
                  <l>QUae tenerum (quondam) ſolita eſt, &amp; inutile gramen</l>
                  <l>Et flores agri, carpere falce levi,</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151189:31"/>
                  <l>Robora, ſublimes <hi>CEDROS VITES<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> ſecuri</l>
                  <l>Fatal, Nunc Mors Improba ſternit humi.</l>
                  <l>Atque uno (ut miſeros, &amp; per compendia reddat)</l>
                  <l>Ict u, Stravit totum hoc genus arboreum.</l>
                  <l>En cui Robur erat <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, CEDRI<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> perennis</l>
                  <l>Durities, <hi>VIT IS</hi> Laetificae Bonitas,</l>
                  <l>Hunc celeri &amp; caeco ſuccidit Vulnere. Caſum</l>
                  <l>Flebit Poſteritas. Nos ſatis haud fuimus.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>In Engliſh thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>DEath, that was wont the tender graſſe to mowe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And crop with gentle Sithe, the flowers that growe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In broidered fields, now fells our ſtouteſt</hi> OAKES,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tall</hi> CEDARS, CHOICEST VINES <hi>with fatal ſtroaks;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And to compleat our miſery, at one blow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>ALL <hi>theſe in</hi> ONE <hi>fierce Death did overthrow.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For Him in whom the</hi> STRENGTH <hi>of</hi> OAKES <hi>did reſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>BEAUTY <hi>of</hi> CEDARS, <hi>and of</hi> VINES <hi>the</hi> BEST:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By a ſwift ſecret ſtroke too, envious Death,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Out of our ſacred Grove removed hath.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus</hi> VINES <hi>cut down, and' cauſe we for his fall</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cannot lament enough, our children ſhall.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M.N.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>Epitaphium, In Diſputatorem acutiſſimum, Concionatorem foeliciſſimum, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologum Eximium, Dominum RICHARD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M VINES.</head>
            <l>QUo diſputante Nemo Nervoſior</l>
            <l>Et <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Strophas ſolvere</l>
            <l>Atque <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> capiſtrare potis magè.</l>
            <l>Quo perorante Nemo facundior,</l>
            <l>Doctior aut, Coelum effundere in Mortaleis</l>
            <l>Sinus, aut Mortalia in Coelum Pectora.</l>
            <l>Quo vivente Nemo charior</l>
            <l>Aut ſuis, aut Amicis veritatis.</l>
            <l>Quo moriente, Ah —</l>
            <l>Deſiderantur plurima.</l>
            <bibl>Poſuit <hi>Mat. Newcomen.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:151189:32"/>
            <head>Upon the much <hi>lamemed Death</hi> of that eminently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed Man of God, Mr. <hi>Richard Vines,</hi> late Paſtor of <hi>Lawrence-Jury, London.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 24.3.</note>
                  <hi>OF figs two baskets,</hi> and two ſorts of <hi>Vines,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some <hi>good,</hi> ſome <hi>bad</hi> I reade; unlike their wines.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32 32.</note>
                  <hi>The Vine of Sodom,</hi> poiſonous grapes which beares,</l>
               <l>The Vine of <hi>Sibmah</hi> bleeding briny teares;</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 16 8. Jer 48.32. 2 Kings 4.39. Hoſ. 101. Job 15.33. Eſa. 5.2. Ezek. 17.6.7.</note>The <hi>wilde Vine</hi> which the Prophets Pot did taint;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An empty Vine,</hi> the foule <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> Saint;</l>
               <l>A <hi>blaſted Vine,</hi> which <hi>unripe fruits</hi> did caſt;</l>
               <l>A <hi>ſoure grap'd Vine,</hi> unpleaſing to the taſte;</l>
               <l>A <hi>bending Vine,</hi> conſtant to no one ſide,</l>
               <l>But changing <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Faiths</hi> with every tide.</l>
               <l>Such were the <hi>old falſe prophets,</hi> curſed ſouies</l>
               <l>Which poiſoned their times with <hi>Hell-brew'd Boules;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such Hypocrites; ſuch the Apoſtate Race;</l>
               <l>Foul Covenant-breakers. Men of no <hi>heart, All-face.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek 17 15.</note>
                  <hi>None ſuch was this our Vines.</hi> A better kinde</l>
               <l>Then thoſe forenam'd you do in Scripture finde.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 2.21. Gen. 49.11. Judg. 9.13. Pſal. 128.3. 1 Kings 4.25. Pſal. 80.15. Ezek 17.8. John 15.</note>
                  <hi>A noble Vine</hi> I meet with, a <hi>Vine choice;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>fruitful Vine,</hi> beſt Embleme of <hi>Increaſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>ſhady Vine,</hi> Enſigne of <hi>publike peace;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Vine of <hi>Gods</hi> own <hi>planting; Goodly Vine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Branches</hi> implanted in a <hi>Vine Divine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such was our Vines,</hi> whoſe noble <hi>fruit,</hi> choice <hi>ſhade</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The gracious heart and ſpirit <hi>chearful</hi> made,</l>
               <l>A Branch of the <hi>True Vine, ingraffed, dreſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By th' <hi>Fathers</hi> hand, <hi>purged, made fruitful, bleſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 15.1, 2, 5.</note>With many Cluſters, full of ſuch rich wine,</l>
               <l>As did <hi>Braines, Hearts,</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> of men refine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh <hi>Noble</hi> Plant! Oh Plant of much renown,</l>
               <l>Loaden with ſo much fruit, as well might crown</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> many Miniſters,</hi> where ſuch variety</l>
               <l>Of Learning, Wiſdom, Courage, Grace and Piety</l>
               <l>Were manag'd with that skill, and ſo improved,</l>
               <l>As made him <hi>honour'd, awed, reverend, loved.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:151189:32"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> conſider! Thy <hi>Vineyard</hi> faſt declines,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>hedge</hi> is broke, <hi>wall</hi> fallen, thy <hi>choiceſt Vines</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tranſplanted are,</hi> now like an <hi>Heath</hi> forlorne</l>
               <l>With <hi>ſtones</hi> thou cover'd art, o're-<hi>run</hi> with <hi>thorne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 5. Pſal. 80.13. Cant. 2.15. Pſal. 80.14.</note>Peſter'd with <hi>briars;</hi> the <hi>Beaſt, Fox</hi> and <hi>wilde Bore</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Do all aſſault thee, and will more and more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>look down Lord from Heaven,</hi> and <hi>viſit</hi> thou</l>
               <l>This <hi>Vineyard</hi> ('tis <hi>thine own</hi>) in danger now;</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 5.</note>The <hi>ſtones</hi> and <hi>thornes</hi> pick out; the <hi>hedge</hi> and <hi>wall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reſtore, <hi>tower</hi> build; but above all</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 27.3.</note> Let thy <hi>eye</hi> be upon it <hi>night</hi> and <hi>day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whatever may it hurt chaſe thou away.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <head>To the Honourable Memory of Mr. <hi>Richard Vines.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>BUt why ſo ſoon, why make ſuch haſte away?</l>
            <l>Could'ſt thou not brook a little more delay,</l>
            <l>And give ſome warning of ſo ſad a blow,</l>
            <l>No private, but a common overthrow?</l>
            <l>As when the Fabrick of ſome ſtately Towre</l>
            <l>Comes near the period of its fatal houre;</l>
            <l>Here ſhrinks a rafter, there a pillar groanes,</l>
            <l>And all the parts breath out their farewel moanes,</l>
            <l>That ſo ſome juſt and ſeaſonable feare,</l>
            <l>May the indwellers for the ſtroke prepare.</l>
            <l>And was it thine intent to verifie</l>
            <l>What we thought falſe, <hi>that Seraphims may die?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Sure could they die, juſt ſo they'd loſe their breath,</l>
            <l>Nor would they pray againſt a ſudden death:</l>
            <l>What was the cauſe thou waſt ſo hurried hence,</l>
            <l>Nor with a moments ſtay would death diſpence?</l>
            <l>Was it becauſe that reſtleſſe helliſh crew</l>
            <l>Did with good Angels their diſpute renew</l>
            <l>'Bout <hi>Moſes</hi> body, and th' Archangel choſe</l>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151189:33"/>
            <l>Thee for his Second to confute his foes,</l>
            <l>Or did thoſe bleſſed ſpirits, (who uſe to pry</l>
            <l>And ſearch into the Goſpel-myſtery)</l>
            <l>Come to a riddle, and reſolved thus</l>
            <l>To ſend for thee to be their <hi>Oedipus?</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Were it not heatheniſh to apprehend</l>
            <l>Mortals could to a Deity aſcend,</l>
            <l>I ſhould expound thy ſudden change to bliſs</l>
            <l>A token of thine <hi>Apotheoſis:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As <hi>Romulus,</hi> when to be deifi'd,</l>
            <l>He muſt to Heaven in a whirlwinde ride.</l>
            <l>Or was't becauſe had a more lingring death</l>
            <l>Giv'n timely notice of thy paſſing breath,</l>
            <l>Such rivers would have flowen from mortal eyes,</l>
            <l>As might the world with a new flood ſurprize.</l>
            <l>Or elſe like <hi>Niobe:</hi> ſuch had been our moan,</l>
            <l>That all mankinde had wept into a ſtone.</l>
            <l>But now amazement did our tears ſuppreſſe,</l>
            <l>And made our grief the more, but danger leſſe.</l>
            <l>Forraign Geographers did once ſurmize,</l>
            <l>That <hi>England</hi> had three Univerſities;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>London</hi> was one: but now they'l change their tone.</l>
            <l>'Tis now too true, <hi>England</hi> hath leſſe by one;</l>
            <l>O you <hi>Caligula</hi>'s, whoſe monſtrous rage</l>
            <l>Could wiſh that all the <hi>Levites</hi> of this Age</l>
            <l>Had but one neck, that ſo one bloody ſword</l>
            <l>Might cut off all the conduits of the Word.</l>
            <l>Forbear, 'tis done, and here doth bleeding lie</l>
            <l>As in a Map all <hi>Englands</hi> Miniſtry.</l>
            <l>You brood of <hi>Munſter,</hi> whoſe prodigious ire</l>
            <l>Deſtines all Libraries unto the fire.</l>
            <l>Surceaſe your barbarous rage, within one ſpan</l>
            <l>Here lies the aſhes of the <hi>Vatican.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>When <hi>Lambeth</hi>-Sea of Books was to forſake</l>
            <l>Its ancient Seat, and a new Chanel take,</l>
            <l>Our Senate did eſpouſe thoſe choice remaines,</l>
            <l>To <hi>Sion</hi>-Houſe, <hi>Cambridge</hi> forbade the banes.</l>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:151189:33"/>
            <l>'Twas doubtful where that walking Library</l>
            <l>Would fixe: both places were reſolv'd to try</l>
            <l>Their titles, but at laſt did thus agree</l>
            <l>To ſend it to the Univerſitie</l>
            <l>Upon theſe termes; they ſhould with <hi>Vines</hi> diſpenſe</l>
            <l>And ſend him hither for a recompence.</l>
            <l>He was tranſplantad; Thus our common mother</l>
            <l>Found one vaſt Library, and loſt another.</l>
            <l>Or if you pleaſe, you may compound it thus:</l>
            <l>They got the ſhadow, th'ſubſtance came to us.</l>
            <l>Some blam'd the publike body of the Nation</l>
            <l>Becauſe they did not call a Convocation;</l>
            <l>They ſent for <hi>Vines,</hi> and what need further coſt?</l>
            <l>In him a whole Aſſembly was ingroſt.</l>
            <l>It could not then be ſaid to <hi>Englands</hi> ſhame</l>
            <l>It hath no Synods, for ſuch was thy fame,</l>
            <l>That in thy Head as in a Common Hall</l>
            <l>They ſaw, they heard a Councel general.</l>
            <l>Some ſay that <hi>Englands</hi> preſent Miniſtry</l>
            <l>Is nothing but an Antichriſtian fry,</l>
            <l>Then ſure thou was't the Pope, for 'twas confeſt</l>
            <l>Thou hadſt all Lawes i'th' Cabinet of thy breaſt.</l>
            <l>But peace, my whining Muſe, and ſay no more</l>
            <l>Of unknown worth, conceal his hidden ſtore.</l>
            <l>Bury the reſt, leſt mortals too much prize</l>
            <l>His ſacred reliques, and idolatrize.</l>
            <l>Leſt other Students, when his parts they hear,</l>
            <l>Grow negligent, and ſink into deſpair.</l>
            <l>Do but name <hi>Vines,</hi> more need not be expreſt,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Tagus</hi> and <hi>Ganges</hi> will report the reſt,</l>
            <l>Each echo at the mention of his name</l>
            <l>Will be a ſounding Trumpet of his fame.</l>
            <l>Sure, that at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> will ſpeak his renown</l>
            <l>Oftner then the echo at <hi>Pont-charentoon.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mat. Pool. Min. of M. Quern. Lond.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:151189:34"/>
            <head>On the ſudden and unexpected death of that famous and incomparable Preacher of the Goſpel, Mr. <hi>Richard Vines.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>I'me pleaſ'd much more to ſee a <hi>Vine,</hi> though weak,</l>
            <l>Laden with cluſters, and its branches break</l>
            <l>With weight of Grapes, then view a ſturdy tree,</l>
            <l>Barren, though ſtanding to eternity.</l>
            <l>A knife that cuts the ſheath I'le rather chuſe,</l>
            <l>Though't wear apace, then that's not fit for uſe.</l>
            <l>A brave man's gone, but this ſhall be my ſtrife,</l>
            <l>Juſt ſo to live, though ſo I end my life.</l>
            <l>My Fancy runs too flat; for every line</l>
            <l>Should yield a flavour of the ſprightly Vine;</l>
            <l>I would not drop a crabby tear on's Herſe,</l>
            <l>Eager devotion martyrs him in verſe.</l>
            <l>Yet farewel mirth. Juſt reaſon for complaint,</l>
            <l>When <hi>Vines</hi> are dead, no wonder if we faint:</l>
            <l>Nothing but Cypreſſe penſive heads ſhall dreſſe,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Vineyard</hi> is become a wilderneſſe.</l>
            <l>Soure grapes there are, I know, in every hedge,</l>
            <l>But he who eats them ſets his teeth on edge.</l>
            <l>Thy grapes were ripe (pure ſoul) ſo that the Preſſe</l>
            <l>Was needleſſe, ſince the ſtreams of happineſſe</l>
            <l>Ran from thee freely, and thou didſt diſtill</l>
            <l>The bleſſed dictates of thy Makers Will.</l>
            <l>For ſoules inflam'd with luſt; Thy Art divine</l>
            <l>Afforded water when they long'd for wine,</l>
            <l>And where a ſoul lay proſtrate with deſpair</l>
            <l>Thy wine prov'd <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> cordial, rare:</l>
            <l>Milk unto babes, ſtrong meat to manly ſtature,</l>
            <l>Thy doctrine ſympathiz'd with every nature.</l>
            <l>Thus the <hi>Vine</hi> flouriſh'd, till a ſoveraign fate</l>
            <l>In Paradiſe did it innoculate.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. Jacombe, Mary Woolnoth Lombardſtreet.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:151189:34"/>
            <head>Upon the never enough to be lamented Death of the learned Mr. <hi>Richard Vines.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>AMongſt the throng of Mourners who do come</l>
               <l>To wait upon the learned <hi>Vines</hi> his tombe;</l>
               <l>Make room (I pray) for one, who with lame verſe</l>
               <l>Can only crawle to offer at his Herfe.</l>
               <l>My muſe (like <hi>Croeſus</hi> ſon) was faſt tongue-ti'd,</l>
               <l>And had ne're ſpoke, had not his father di'd.</l>
               <l>Let her but groan to eaſe her heart, and then</l>
               <l>She ſhall give over, and be dumb agen.</l>
               <l>Oh you his people, let your ſorrow ſwell</l>
               <l>To floods of tears, which to'th'world may tell</l>
               <l>Your loſſe, and when y'have wept your eyes quite dry,</l>
               <l>Let him be wept by your poſterity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How have we angred Heaven? what ugly ſin</l>
               <l>Hath in this wretched City harbour'd been?</l>
               <l>What whoredoms, murders, and Heaven-daring crimes</l>
               <l>Have broken out in theſe debautched times?</l>
               <l>That we ſhould live to ſee the angry hand</l>
               <l>Of God ſtretch't out againſt our Church and Land.</l>
               <l>Breaking our pillars down with furious haſte,</l>
               <l>Laying our well compact foundations waſte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Powerful <hi>Whitaker,</hi> whoſe inceſſant cries</l>
               <l>Did reach the Heavens, and laid ſiege to th'skies.</l>
               <l>Reverend <hi>Gataker;</hi> whoſe unfathom'd braine</l>
               <l>Did all the Arts and Sciences contain.</l>
               <l>Laborious <hi>Robinſon,</hi> whoſe care and pain</l>
               <l>Was for immortal ſoules, not wealth or gain.</l>
               <l>Stout-hearted <hi>Love,</hi> who durſt defie the axe,</l>
               <l>When others yielded like the melting waxe;</l>
               <l>Theſe are no more, and to compleat our wo,</l>
               <l>Eloquent <hi>Vines</hi> ſtoops to deaths fatal blow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Have patience (Gentlemen) and tithes abhor'd</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Patron.</note>Will lapſed be unto the preſent Lord.</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151189:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>You need not beat your braines how to lay waſte</l>
               <l>Our pious Clergy; See, with ſpeed they haſte</l>
               <l>To get into their Ark, before the cloud</l>
               <l>(That gathers thick) poure down in ſhowers of blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thus our glorious Lights waſte and expire,</l>
               <l>For all our new ones we may ſink i'th' mire</l>
               <l>Of damn'd Apoſtacy, that horrid crime</l>
               <l>Which threatens ruine to our preſent time.</l>
               <l>Oh for an <hi>Atlas</hi> to uphold the Sphear</l>
               <l>Of our reeling Church, which frighted. ſhakes with fear</l>
               <l>I could my ſelf turn Seeker, (but 'tis vain)</l>
               <l>Another ſturdy reſolute <hi>Vines</hi> to gain;</l>
               <l>He whoſe undaunted courage did contend</l>
               <l>With blaſphemies and errours to his end</l>
               <l>No armed vice, or wickedneſſe in buffe,</l>
               <l>No ſcarlet ſinners gown, or chain, or ruffe,</l>
               <l>Could fright him to baſe ſilence, no ſweet bait</l>
               <l>With a hook in it, but he ſcorn'd it ſtrait.</l>
               <l>Rather then ſwear, that which his ſoul did dread,</l>
               <l>He loſt his Headſhip — would have loſt his Head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>Eſſex</hi> fell, our Nations glory;</l>
               <l>Who but Seraphick <hi>Vines</hi> muſt tell his ſtory?</l>
               <l>The drooping State that did attend his fall,</l>
               <l>When Lords and Commons wept his Funeral;</l>
               <l>The mourning drum, the Lance and Enſignes trail'd,</l>
               <l>The robes of honour all in Sables vail'd</l>
               <l>Did but affect the eye, 'twas only he,</l>
               <l>Who tun'd our hearts into ſad melody:</l>
               <l>His tongue and pen eterniz'd <hi>Eſſex</hi> more,</l>
               <l>Then all the trophies which his tombe then wore;</l>
               <l>And this will ſound our learned <hi>Vines</hi> his praiſe,</l>
               <l>Louder then riming, or our crackling bayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thomas Playre.</hi> Gent.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
